<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theophosoi [sic] theophiloi: God's fearers are God's favourites, or, An encouragement to fear God in the worst times delivered in several sermons / by ... Nath. Tucker ...</title>
            <author>Tucker, Nath.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3209A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875941</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2297:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theophosoi [sic] theophiloi: God's fearers are God's favourites, or, An encouragement to fear God in the worst times delivered in several sermons / by ... Nath. Tucker ...</title>
                  <author>Tucker, Nath.</author>
                  <author>Kentish, Richard.</author>
                  <author>Whitfield, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the Christian reader" signed: Richard Kentish; "An epistle to the reader" signed: Tho. Whitfield.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sion College Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Malachi III, 16-18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fear of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Θεόροβοι Θεόριλοι: GODS FEARERS ARE GODS FAVOURITES.</p>
            <p>OR, AN Encouragement To fear GOD IN The worſt TIMES.</p>
            <p>Delivered in ſeveral Sermons, by that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Servant of Chriſt, <hi>Nath. Tucker,</hi> late Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>Portſmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 8.12.</hi>
               </bibl> Surely, I know it ſhall be well with them that fear God, that fear before him.</q>
            <q>Timor praeſens ſecuritatem generat ſempiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Timenti Dominum bene erit in extremis, <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern. de Tim. Dei.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>Dorman New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> at the Kings Armes in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> next to <hi>Grocers-Ally.</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152468:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152468:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>IT was the ſaying of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to <hi>Abimelech,</hi> Gen. 20.11. <hi>Becauſe I thought ſurely the fear of God is not in this place, they will ſlay me for my wifes ſake.</hi> Where the Fear of GOD is wanting, what E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil will not Men commit? Where this Bank is broken down, the Floods of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Wickedneſs will flow over. Hence it is, That in
<pb facs="tcp:152468:3"/>our Age, many turn Atheiſts, run to all manner of Exceſs of Riot, play the Apoſtates, grow faint-hearted in the Cauſe of God, are afraid of Men: and as the <hi>Burgundians once were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid all the Reeds they ſaw, had been Launces;</hi> ſo theſe fear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing they ſee, yea, their own ſhadows: and all this is for want of the Fear of God. <hi>Meritò omnia timet, qui illum non timet.</hi> It is therefore very proper Work for us to preſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Fear. It is called, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor Animae,</hi> The Porter to keep out the Soul's Foes, and to let in the Soul's Friends. It is <hi>Principium &amp; Praecipuum
<pb facs="tcp:152468:3"/>Sapientiae,</hi> The Beginning and Perfection of Wiſdom; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fit to be purſued after. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ſpeech of the Lord concerning <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. 5.29. <hi>O that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would fear me.</hi> Shall God wiſh it, and ſhall not men preſs after it? yet ſuch is our averſeneſs to that which is good, that Precept upon Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and Line upon Line will ſcarce perſwade us.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Author of this enſuing Tract, hath taken great paines to promote that which the Lord doth ſo pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically wiſh for. Read dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently therefore what is here
<pb facs="tcp:152468:4"/>written, and thou mayſt gain much by it. Here thou wilt finde ſome Diſcoveries of this Fear, ſome Motives to preſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and ſome Helps to obtain it; all handled in a moſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and melting manner: and that a Bleſsing may go along with this Diſcourſe, in order to thy eternal Benefit, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy ſouls well-wiſher,</hi> Richard Kentiſh.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 13. 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epistle_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152468:4"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE To the READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ALthough my Approbation can add little weight to the worth of this enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; yet being deſired to ſhew kindneſs to the Dead, in giving a true Teſtimony to this Poſthumous Piece, I could not refuſe to perform ſuch an Office of Love, as by the Rule of Love we are all obliged unto. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may truely ſay, That having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed it, I finde nothing in it but that which is ſound, holy and wholeſome, fit to inform the Judgement, and to raiſe holy Reſolutions and Affections in the Hearts of the Readers,
<pb facs="tcp:152468:5"/>fweetly breathing forth Piety in every Paſſage of it: ſo that whoſoever will give it the reading over, (which will quickly be done) ſhall have cauſe not to think his Time miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent: But (if his Heart be in a right Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) he ſhall finde it hereby more ſtirred with deſire to get to be amongſt the number of thoſe true Fearers of God, for whom, a loving Record and a Book of Merciful Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſhall be written for their ſhelter in evil Times, that they may finde Mercy in the evil day; for which times, our good God fit and prepare us all. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Whitfeld.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152468:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAL. 3.16, 17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another; and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name.</p>
                  <p>And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of hosts, in that day when I make up my jewels; and I will ſpare him, as a man ſpareth his own ſon that ſerveth him.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall ye return, and diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Muſt firſt give you ſome light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the context, and then come unto the words of the text: <hi>Then they that feared the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The particle <hi>az, Then,</hi> in the front of the text, carries us back to the conſideration of the coherence.</p>
            <p>The godly here, having this character given
<pb facs="tcp:152468:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152468:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152468:7"/>them, <hi>They that feared the Lord,</hi> were (as it ſeems) reſerved to thoſe laſt and looſeſt times of the Jewiſh Church, after the return from <hi>Babylon;</hi> where the ſeventy years captivity had not much reformed or amended the major part of the Jews. Gods correcting hand had lain a long time ſore heavie upon them; but God had not his end upon this untoward generation: theſe unſanctified perſons grew worſe and worſe with afflictions; witneſs their blaſphemous words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my text, where they ſtand ſtouting it out with the Lord of hoſts, verſ. 13. <hi>Your words have been ſtout againſt me, ſaith the Lord: yet ye ſay, What have we ſpoken ſo much againſt thee?</hi> They ſtick not to charge God with deep oſcitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and neglect of his beſt ſervants, (verſ. 14.) as if they ſhould reap no fruit from the ſervice of God; as if all their labour were in vain: yea indeed, they tax God of flat iniquity, and moſt unequal adminiſtrations, verſ. 15. <hi>And now we call the proud happie: yea, they that work wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are ſet up; yea, they that tempt God are even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</hi> As if they had ſaid, Surely there is no reward for the righteous, verily there is not a God that doth judge in the earth: the proud, who tempt God, and trample upon his people, they are not onely not puniſhed, but even pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd and advanced for their labour: either things are not ordered by a divine providence, but left at random, let run at ſixes and ſevens; or elſe there is not an even or equal hand held over the ſons of men, but partiality and unrighteouſneſs found in God. Thus theſe miſcreants in their madneſs ſet their mouthes againſt heaven, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152468:7"/>ſpared not deſpitefully to ſpit their venom in the face of God himſelf. At the hearing of which horrid and abhorred blaſphemies, the godly of theſe times are much affected; they met often about it, and not without a great deal of good conference: <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another.</hi> Then? when? Why whiles the wicked did blaſpheme, and belch out their impieties againſt God; even at that inſtant and juncture of time, <hi>they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another.</hi> Thus briefly of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence.</p>
            <p>The whole text may be divided into theſe two main or general branches:
<list>
                  <item>1. A duty performed.</item>
                  <item>2. A mercy returned upon the performance of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The duty performed lies in the beginning of the text, even in theſe words: <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another.</hi> Which duty is illuſtrated or ſet forth two ways:
<list>
                  <item>1. In the circumſtances of it.</item>
                  <item>2. In the matter and ſubſtance of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the circumſtances; and they are two:
<list>
                  <item>1. Of Time.</item>
                  <item>2. Of Perſons.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of time: <hi>Then: Then they,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of perſons: They were ſuch as <hi>feared the Lord, and thought upon his Name;</hi> as you ſee in the beginning and concluſion of verſ. 16.</p>
            <p>And then the duty is illuſtrated in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſubſtance of it; and that was frequent mutual conference; they ſpake often one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152468:8"/>
               <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the firſt general branch: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is a mercy returned; and that is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Gods gracious acceptation;
<list>
                  <item>1. In that for the preſent he regarded and reſpected what they did: <hi>The Lord heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and heard it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. In that for the future he regiſtred or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded it: <hi>And a book of remembrance was written before him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, His righteous remuneration or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution,
<list>
                  <item>1. Of mercy to his people: which reflects
<list>
                        <item>1. Upon their perſons.</item>
                        <item>2. Upon their performances.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Upon their perſons, which he will
<list>
                        <item>1. Own: <hi>They ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Honour: <hi>In that day when I make up my jewels.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This mercy reſpects their perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, in paſſing by the weakneſſes, defects, and failings of them: <hi>I will ſpare them as a man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, you have Gods juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous retribution of judgement unto his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, verſ. 18. <hi>Then ſhall ye return, and diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you have likewiſe briefly heard both the Diviſion and Subdiviſion of the Text.</p>
            <p>There is yet one thing more which I muſt wade thorow, before I proceed on to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and that is Explication.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152468:8"/>Now that I may make way unto the Doctrine the ſooner, I ſhall open the 16 verſe onely, and the two other verſes when I come to the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them.</p>
            <p>Well then, firſt of the 16 verſe: <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another: and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a book of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Hebrew we read it thus: <hi>Az nidhbaru jirra Jehovah iſh El raganaha: Then they fearing God, ſpake often man</hi> (or <hi>every man</hi>) <hi>to his neighbour</hi> (or <hi>companion.</hi>) For though the Hebrew word for <hi>ſpake,</hi> in the conjugation <hi>Kal</hi> notes a bare ſpeaking; yet in the conjugation <hi>Niphal, ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis continuationem ſeu frequentationem ſignificat;</hi> it ſignifies the continuation or frequencie of their ſpeaking one to another: they did not do it onely once or twice, but they did it <hi>often: Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another.</hi> Thoſe few names that had not defiled their garments in ſo foul a ſeaſon, but had kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted of the world, they <hi>ſpake often, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some render the text, <hi>Tunc vaſtati ſunt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes Domini, ſc. ab impiis &amp; atheis impunè eos invadentibus:</hi> i. e. <hi>Then were thoſe that feared the Lord waſted and deſtroyed,</hi> viz. <hi>by thoſe atheiſts, who fell from fierce words to bloudy blows.</hi> And the reaſon of this verſion or reading is, becauſe the word <hi>dibhi</hi> in the text, in the conjugation <hi>Pihel,</hi> is rendered to <hi>kill,</hi> or to <hi>deſtroy.</hi> But I conceive that this is far fet, and nothing ſo agreeable unto the minde of the holy Ghoſt, as our Tranſlation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152468:9"/>is. For, 1. 'Tis not <hi>dibberu</hi> in <hi>Pihel,</hi> but <hi>nidh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beru</hi> in <hi>Niphal.</hi> Beſides, this reading is not ſo anſwerable to the following words.</p>
            <p>I, but you will ask me, What did theſe men fearing the Lord ſpeak, when they ſpake ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten one to another?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stock</hi> in his Expoſition upon <hi>Malachi,</hi> and ſome others, think the words following to be theirs, and not God's words; who, they ſay, ſpeaking not until the 17 verſe, in comforting one another, they ſaid, <hi>The Lord hearkned and heard,</hi> &amp;c. But for my part, I rather incline to thoſe who tell us, that the Prophet hath not in expreſs words declared what theſe men fearing the Lord ſpake one to another; onely in telling us that they ſpake one to another, and by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to the ungodly of that time, it muſt be ſuppoſed that they ſpake good and gracious things: they ſtood up to ſtickle for God, to ſtop the mouth of Blaſphemy, and to eſtabliſh one another in the perſwaſion of Gods holy Truth, and conſtant care of his own children. Thoſe wicked ones did not ſpeak ſo much againſt God, againſt his providence and government, as they did for God, in defence of his providence and government. And this they did for mutual ſtrengthening and confirmation, that that which was haply halting might not be turned out of the way, but healed rather; that they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm each other againſt thoſe great and grievous temptations which lay in their way.</p>
            <p>It followeth: <hi>And the Lord hearkned, and heard it.</hi> Did they whiſper ſo in one anothers ear, that no ear elſe heard them? No: <hi>the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152468:9"/>hearkned, and heard it;</hi> the Lord liſtened, as it were, at the key-hole; he was under the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. The word <hi>jachebil</hi> in the Original, <hi>he hearkned,</hi> comes from a root which ſignifies to attend and lift up the ear: <hi>Geſtus eſt diligenter auſcultantis;</hi> 'tis the geſture of one that heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth diligently: and ſo the word is taken, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 52.3. the later part of the verſe: i. e. <hi>They ſhall diligently hearken</hi> Nay, the word imports not onely attention of body, but attention of minde; as when a man liſteneth as for life, and makes hard ſhift to hear all: thus <hi>the Lord hearkned, and heard;</hi> the Lord did diligently obſerve what they ſaid, and what they did: nothing drops from them, but the Lord attentively regards it. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: and the Lord hearkned and heard it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And a book of remembrance was written before him.</hi> In the Hebrew we read it thus: <hi>And there was written a book of memory before his face.</hi> We read in Scripture of a threefold book of God. The firſt is a book of his reſolved Decree: of this we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. Saith <hi>Moſes</hi> there, <hi>Yet now, if thou wilt, forgive their ſin; and if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of thy book, which thou hast written.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.28. So in many other texts, where by <hi>book</hi> we are to underſtand the book of Gods Decree, or Pre-ordination. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, there is a book of Gods acted Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.16. <hi>Thine eyes did ſee my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance yet being unperfect, and in thy book all my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were written,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> in thy book of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Now this later is but a tranſcript or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of the former. Thoſe huge original volumes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152468:10"/>of love and bleſſings which he hath laid up in his heart for his own people; thoſe alſo of wrath and judgment which he hath laid up there againſt his enemies from all eternity: thoſe volumes (I ſay) of love or wrath are writing out every day, by the hand and pen of Providence. But then thirdly, there is a book of love, and of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8. <hi>Thou tellest my wanderings: put thou my tears into thy bottle; are they not in thy book?</hi> i. e. in thy book of remembrance. And this latter (Beloved) is the book ſpoken of here in my text. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another; and the Lord hearkened, and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him:</hi> Liber monumenti, A Book of Acts and Monuments; ſo ſome render it, in alluſion unto the cuſtom of Kings, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.23. latter part: <hi>And it was written in the book of the chronicles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the king. Tamerlain,</hi> that warlike Scythian, of whom you read in the Turkiſh Hiſtory, had always by him a catalogue of the names and good deſerts of his ſervants, which he daily peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and whom he duely rewarded; not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by them, or by any others in their behalf, to be put in remembrance. Thus (Beloved) God (if I may ſo ſpeak) files up the prayers of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, puts all their ſpeeches as well as practices upon record, that he may make all honourable mention of them at the laſt day, in the General Aſſembly of heaven. <hi>Liber Commentarii,</hi> a book of Commentaries, ſo <hi>Junius</hi> renders it, where God doth as it were deſcant and comment upon all the holy and gracious ſpeeches and practices of his people. You muſt not underſtand it ſo, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152468:10"/>if God had any ſuch Memorial-book, as if he ſtood in need of it, or were ſubject to forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; no, but 'tis ſpoken <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after the manner of men, who have books to help their memories. God will no more forget the ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry religious diſcourſes of his people, then a man doth that which he hath recorded in his book lying before him: <hi>A book of remembrance was written before him;</hi> before his face. If we ſpeak but a word for God, we ſhall hear of it again: God takes it and pens it down: he ſets it down preſently; all was kept upon record. As when they who do not fear the Lord ſpeak one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, when wicked men plot againſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, or conſpire againſt the holy ways of God, God hearkneth and heareth, and there is a book of remembrance kept of it; let them whiſper as ſoftly as they can, God can hear, and will record all their malicious ſpeeches, all their evil devices and contrivements, whether againſt himſelf, or againſt his ſervants: ſo on the other ſide, when <hi>they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another,</hi> in the juſtification of his ways, in the vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his providence, <hi>the Lord hearkned and heard; and a book of remembrance was written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</hi> Of the two, 'tis better expreſt by a book, then by words: for that which is written, is more durable and permanent; whereas things ſpoken many times vaniſh, and are blown away in the air, and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>Well then, in the laſt place, we will conſider in whoſe behalf this book of remembrance was written: it was, you ſee, <hi>for them that feared the Lord, and thought upon his Name. For them that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152468:11"/>feared the Lord;</hi> of that character of the godly ſpake ſomething but even now: <hi>and that though upon his Name;</hi> a word or two onely of this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet or character. The word in the Origina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here uſed, is derived from a word which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies not ſimply or barely to think, but to ſet the head and heart on work about that which we think upon. It carries the intention of the mind with it. <hi>And that thought upon his Name:</hi> i. e. that had God before their eyes, that minded his glory, that thought upon his Commandments to do them; thoſe are the perſons for whom a book of remembrance was written before the Lord.</p>
            <p>And thus have I at length finiſhed the Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the Diviſion and Explication of the text. Before I proceed to open the ſubſequent verſes, I ſhall enquire what Obſervations may be made upon, and Deductions gathered from this 16 verſe which I have already opened.</p>
            <p>And here firſt of all, I ſhall take into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the connexive or copulative particle <hi>Then</hi> in the beginning of the verſe: <hi>THEN they that foared the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Then? When? Why in thoſe looſer and more degenerated times, when men were arrived to that height of impudency and profaneſs, as to ſay, it was to no purpoſe to ſerve God: then when their black mouthes were ſwoln big with their blaſphemies; <hi>THEN they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another:</hi> they ſpake of God, and for God; they then ſtood up in the vindication of his ways and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations. So that (Beloved) from hence I ſhall note this Point; namely,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152468:11"/>
               <hi>That the ſervants of God muſt labour to ſhew themſelves beſt in the worſt times.</hi> When others were moſt againſt God, and contrary unto him, then muſt they be moſt ſtirring and active for God, moſt diligent and careful in his buſineſs. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of which Point, I ſhall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Method in this faſhion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall confirm the Point by precept.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Commend this duty, from the conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the people of God in all Ages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Clear it up, upon ſome grounds and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conſiderations.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, make ſome improvement of it unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed upon theſe ſeveral Heads, ſo far as the ordinary time will permit; beginning with thoſe expreſs precepts which are ſcattered up and down in the Scriptures to this very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. We will content our ſelves with three or four. The one is <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil.</hi> Some whereof are ſet down by way of negation, ſome by way of affirmation. The way to hell is broad, and much beaten. <hi>Per viam publicam non ingredere,</hi> was one of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his precepts: Do not do as the moſt do, leſt thou be undone for ever. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum turpiſſimum turba,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca:</hi> An Argument from the multitude, is not argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative. Nay, you ſee there is here in this text a ſpecial reſtraint put upon it: <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil.</hi> And the Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe man is ſo apt to be led by many: the heart
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152468:12"/>is ready to flatter it ſelf into an opinion, that God will not be very angry when a practice is grown common: this is the courſe of the world, this is the way of moſt men; ſurely there is no great danger in it. Well now, ſaith God, <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil.</hi> A ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond text to this purpoſe, you have, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10, 11, and following verſes: <hi>My ſon, if ſinners en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thee, conſent thou not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>q.d.</hi> Do not cloſe in, or comply with them. And again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Be not conformed to this world.</hi> He doth not ſay, Live not in the world; we muſt live here, until God call us hence: neither doth he ſay, Uſe not the world; for 'tis impoſſible but that whiles we live here, we muſt uſe the world; though we are cautioned to <hi>uſe the world as though we uſed it not:</hi> but, <hi>Be not conformed unto this world.</hi> The word in the Greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date not your ſelves to the world:</hi> ſo <hi>Eraſmus</hi> reads it. <hi>Faſhion not your ſelves to the world:</hi> ſo <hi>Beza.</hi> But in ours, and ſome other Tranſlations, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not,</hi> &amp;c. As a Player is faſhioned to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and words, either of drunkenneſs or adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, when he acteth them on the ſcaffold; that is the true notation of the word. <hi>Be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to this world,</hi> i.e. Do not make the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the world the rule of your life: let not your corrupt mindes, which will carry you after a corrupt world, prevail with you. Now theſe are the precepts which are laid down by way of Negation. I ſhall give you two that are ſet down by way of Affirmation. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.43. ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> there, <hi>Save your ſelves from this untoward generation;</hi> i.e. from the corrupt ſociety of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152468:12"/>And again, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord:</hi> q.d. Do not comply with the corruptions of the world; let all theſe go, whatever you loſe or ſuffer for it. Thus much for the precepts.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I ſhall commend this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto you from the conſtant practice of the people of God, even in all ages. See an inſtance of it, 1. in <hi>Noah:</hi> when the whole earth was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt before God, he walked perfectly &amp; uprightly with God in his generation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Noah</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alone, in a way different from a world of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people; he was moſt ſincere in the ſervice of God, in the darkeſt midnight of damned im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. 2. <hi>Abraham,</hi> pull'd as a brand out of <hi>Ur</hi> of the Caldees, where-ever he came, he ſet up altars to God in the midſt of Idolaters, and makes open profeſſion of his worſhip before the people of the land, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8 So <hi>Joſhua</hi> after him, <hi>Joſh</hi> 24.15. Do you what you will; though you do generally &amp; univerſally ſerve other gods, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> See this in <hi>Elijah,</hi> who was <hi>zealous for the Lord God of hosts,</hi> though alone and ſingular, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.10. I might tell you of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> who <hi>ſeared the Lord greatly,</hi> in a common defection, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. But come we unto the New Teſtament, and let us ſee what practice of this duty we finde there. I ſhall begin with Chriſt, who is the original co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, an infallible unerring example: he was <hi>eaten up</hi> with <hi>the zeal of his Fathers houſe,</hi> when it was polluted and profaned by all ſorts, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16, 17. The Apoſtles after his departure reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to <hi>obey God,</hi> notwithſtanding the menaces
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152468:13"/>of the Councel, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19, 20. <hi>Paul</hi> openly conteſteth with the Gentiles at <hi>Athens</hi> about their fenſleſs ſuperſtition, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.22. <hi>Antipas</hi> held forth the Word of life even unto the death, <hi>where Satans throne was,</hi> Rev. 2.13. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> that bleſſed Martyr of Jeſus Chriſt, who being commanded by the Tyrant to do ſacrifice to the Idol, returns this anſwer: <hi>Eighty and odde years have I ſerved my maſter Chriſt, and he never deceived me; and ſhall I now deſert him? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid me any ſuch wickedneſs. Octoginta ſex annos ills ſervui,</hi> &amp;c. It were eaſie to come lower, and nearer our own times, and to produce a whole cloud of ſuch who held forth the Word of life by a bold and wiſe profeſſion in the darkneſs of Popery. But I will give you one onely inſtance more, and then conclude: it was <hi>Athanaſtus,</hi> that notable champion of Chriſt, who ſtood ſtoutly to the defence of the Truth, when all the Chriſtian world beſide was turned Arrian: <hi>Ille v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r totius orbis impetum ſustinuit:</hi> the whole world was ſet againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> againſt the whole world. And thus you have heard how the force-mentioned duty hath been practiſed by the ſervants of God.</p>
            <p>I come to the Grounds of the Point. If you look either upward or downward, either to God or men, you will finde Reaſon ſufficient for the practice of this duty; all which Reaſons are grounded upon the text, and ſhall be thence ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt, The Reaſons taken from God; and they ſhall be theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God doth exactly obſerve, and graciouſly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152468:13"/>accept of ſuch his ſervants as continue conſtant with him in corrupt and depraved times, in a general defection or declenſion: when ſin is grown uſual, and almoſt epidemical, then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Truths, Ways, and Ordinances of God, Oh how pleaſing and acceptable is this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God! <hi>The Lord hearkned and heard,</hi> (ſaith my Text) God was much taken and affected with thoſe ſweet conferences, thoſe godly dialogues and diſcourſes which dropt from the mouthes of the godly of thoſe times: he <hi>hearkned and heard,</hi> it was melodious and delightful muſick to his heavenly ears, and he doth as it were apply his ears cloſe, he lays them near to their lips, as loth to loſe any part of their holy language: <hi>The lord hearkned and heard.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12, ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>The eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and his ears are open unto their prayers:</hi> or, as 'tis in the Original, <hi>His ears are unto,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>into their prayers:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now what the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of that individual or particular duty of Prayer, is as true of their whole Chriſtian practice: not a prayer which the godly put up, not a good work they do, not a good word which they utter, no not a good thought which they conceive, but the Lords eyes are upon it, and his ears open unto it; he ſets it all down in his Regiſter or Note-book: <hi>A book of remembrance was written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, 2. As the Lord doth graciouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this practice, ſo will he plentifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it: this labour of faith and love ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgotten; it ſhall not onely be entred or ingroſſed in a book of remembrance, but <hi>they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152468:14"/>they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of hosts.</hi> 1. <hi>They ſhall be mine:</hi> i.e. I will not onely own them by a general right, as my creatures; but by a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, peculiar, and diſtinguiſhing title, as my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, my Saints and Servants, ſuch as <hi>have made a covenant with me by ſacrifice; I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people:</hi> I will look upon them as the top of my wealth, and my moſt eſteemed treaſure, as my Jewels, whom I will keep ſafe in the golden Cabinet of my ſpecial providence, and fatherly protection. But this is not all: <hi>I will ſpare them</hi> too, <hi>as a man ſpareth his onely ſon that ſerveth him:</hi> i.e. I will not caſt them out, or reject them, for every ſmall fault, for every flaw or defect in their ſervices, I ſhall give them their allowance, paſs by and over-look their weakneſſes. How effectual (me thinks) might theſe Conſiderations be, to provoke us to a holy contention in godlineſs, when the times are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo bad and boiſterous! Hereby we ſhall pleaſe God, hereby we ſhall procure good unto our ſelves. And thus in brief of the firſt ſort of Reaſons, taken from God.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort reſpect Men: And that 1. Our ſelves: and then 2. Others. 1. Our ſelves. And this I ſhall branch forth into two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By cleaving or ſticking cloſe unto God in corrupt times, we ſhall approve our ſelves, 1. to be holy Chriſtians: 2. to be zealous Chriſtians. Firſt, we ſhall make it appear that we are holy Chriſtians, that we are men and women fearing God. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>Pure religion, and undefiled before God, and the Father, is this, — To keep himſelf unſpotted from the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152468:14"/>world.</hi> When we keep our ſelves unſpotted of the world, and eſcape untainted of it, 'tis an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that our Religion is a pure Religion: a pure life, eſpecially in impure times, argues a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith; it ſignifieth, that <hi>the myſtery of faith is held in a pure conſcience.</hi> We never anſwer Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion better, then when we keep our <hi>way unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19. <hi>There must</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>be errours alſo among you:</hi> there muſt be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in doctrine, and errours in practice; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in judgement, and corruption in life: but why? 'tis becauſe <hi>they which are approved may be made manifest:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Greek is meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical, a Metaphor borrowed from allowance of Coyn: Silver which by the Goldſmiths trial is found good, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i.e.</hi> allowed, good and currant, Evil and corrupt times are diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating and diſtinguiſhing times; then men and women ſhew themſelves what they are, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counterfeit or currant profeſſors: 'Tis then eaſie for men to judge of themſelves, and for others to judge of them. Read <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>That ye may be blameleſs, and harmleſs, the ſons of God, without rebuke, in the midst of a crooked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe nation, among whom ye ſhine as lights in the world.</hi> There muſt be a perverſe and graceleſs generation, a viperous brood, in the midſt of whom Gods Saints muſt ſhine as lamps in the world, that ſo they may approve themſelves blameleſs and harmleſs, the ſons of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke, holding forth the Word of life, when 'tis moſt oppoſed and oppreſt by the ſons of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial.</hi> This now, I ſay, is the property of a man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152468:15"/>that truly fears God; he cannot blow hot and cold, as we uſe to ſay; he dares not ſwear by God and <hi>Malchom;</hi> he will not hide the Truth in indifferency: he knows that God muſt be worſhipped truly, without halting; and totally, without halving. That is the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>But then, 2. As by cleaving unto God, his Truth and Service, in the worſt times, we ſhall approve our ſelves to be holy Chriſtians; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhall we make it appear that we are zealous Chriſtians, ſollicitouſly minding that high &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name of God, whereby we are called. Thus the holy Apoſtles ſtanding before the Council, manifeſted themſelves to be men enflamed with fervent zeal toward the honour of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>We cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard;</hi> we cannot do otherwiſe, we are neceſſitated unto it; being like veſſels, that when they are fill'd and ſtopt up, muſt either vent or break, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. We may ſee this likewiſe in <hi>Paul,</hi> that precious man; when once he become a choſen veſſel to the Lord Chriſt, to bear his Name, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was he ſo mad before, in havocking thoſe that called upon that Name in all places, as he was now fierce and fiery againſt all that did any thing contrary to the Name of Jeſus. <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf to be a zealous Chriſtian: and ſo ſhall we, if we hold faſt and cloſe to God, in looſe and licentious times. Thus much likewiſe of the ſecond ſort of Reaſons, taken from our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The laſt ſort of Reaſons reſpect others; and they ſhall be likewiſe two: the firſt concern
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152468:15"/>the Godly; the ſecond, the Wicked.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby good men ſhall be much confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and comforted, I mean, by our holding out in bad times: this is very effectual for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſtrengthning, and eſtabliſhing of the hands that hang down, and the feeble knees, which it may be otherwiſe would warp, and turn out of the way. Whiles we ceaſe not to <hi>ſpeak</hi> (with theſe in my text) <hi>often one to another,</hi> we <hi>build up one another in our moſt holy faith.</hi> Phil. 1.14. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>And many of the brethren in the Lord waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to ſpeak the word without fear.</hi> Pray mark it, <hi>they waxed confident by my bonds.</hi> By the Apoſtles conſtancie to, and perſeverance in the Truth, in evil and perſecuting times, the Goſpel took deeper rooting and impreſſion in the hearts of many of the Paſtors of the Church: they were ſo far from being diſcouraged by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles bonds, as that they grew bolder then they were before, and durſt more freely to preach and to profeſs the Goſpel. If you look into the <hi>Acts and Monuments,</hi> you ſhall finde what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of confirmation the godly of thoſe times received, by their fellow-brethrens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in the Truth. Well might <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſay, <hi>Conſtantiae Martyrum irrigatur &amp; augetur Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia:</hi> i.e. The Church was enlarged through the conſtancie of the Martyrs. Many inſtances of it might be given, were it neceſſary ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But in the laſt place, <hi>Gods ſervants muſt be beſt in worſt times,</hi> becauſe hereby, as good men ſhall be confirmed, ſo wicked men ſhall be convinced, and even confounded; &amp; that not only in the laſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152468:16"/>great and general Judgement, but in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world alſo. A full proof whereof you have in thoſe two mighty, yet wicked Monarchs, in <hi>Daniel, Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and <hi>Darius.</hi> How was <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> appaled, and even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, when he ſaw the high reſolution and courage of thoſe three Worthies, <hi>Shadrach, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhach</hi> &amp; <hi>Abednego,</hi> in changing the Kings word, and yielding their bodies to be burnt, rather then worſhip a ſtrange god, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3 28. there you may finde it. How was <hi>Darius</hi> amuzed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, when <hi>Daniel</hi> by the ſtrength of his faith had ſtopt the mouthes of the lions, after he had ſtood it out ſtoutly to the face of his adverſaries! How did the innocencie and piety of theſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, triumph in the conſciences of thoſe two Tyrants, making them afraid, and compelling them to vote the ſame way that they had before perſecuted, yea and to proclaim that God for the onely true God, whom yet they had no minde to ſet up for their own God. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29. ſaith <hi>N. buchadnezzar</hi> there, <hi>I make a decree, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry people, nation, and language, which ſpeak any thing amiſs againſt the God of Shadrach, Meſhach, and Abednego, ſhall be cut in pieces, and their houſes ſhall be made a dunghill, becauſe there is no other god that can deliver after this ſort.</hi> And <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.25, 26. ſaith <hi>Darius, I make a decree, that in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dominion of my kingdom, men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel: for he is the living God, and ſtedfaſt for ever, and his kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed, and his dominion ſhall be even unto the end.</hi> 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> that bloudy perſecutor, <hi>Imperium depoſuit quodam mentis ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152468:16"/>&amp; conſternatione, poſt quam ſingularem Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anorum in morte conſtantiam perſpexiſſet:</hi> i. e. That he laid down his Empire with terrour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation of minde, after he had obſerved that height of ſpirit, reſolution and conſtancie which was in the Chriſtians. How did <hi>Steven,</hi> being full of faith and courage, aſtoniſh his adverſaries! The text ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.15. <hi>All that ſate in the council, looking ſtedfaſtly on him, ſaw his face, as it had been the face of an angel.</hi> So true is that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 28.4. <hi>They that forſake the law, praiſe the wicked: but ſuch as keep the law, contend with them.</hi> A godly man, I ſay, that is unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not like a troubled fountain, or a corrupt ſpring, though he may for a time receive evil words from the wicked, yet their hearts are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of him, and their conſciences do admire him.</p>
            <p>And thus (Beloved) you have heard the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Grounds and Reaſons of the Point, as far forth as time will permit. I ſhall make ſome Improvement of it unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>This Point I ſhall apply two ways: 1. for Increpation; and then 2. for Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Increpation, or Reproof. This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine caſts a ſevere aſpect upon two ſorts:
<list>
                  <item>1. Upon all formal and luke-warm <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> upon all temporizing and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt time-ſerving Goſpellers.</item>
                  <item>2. Upon all timerous, fearful, and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Chriſtians.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe: Is it ſo, <hi>That the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God muſt labour to ſhew themſelves best in the worſt times,</hi> that they ſhould ſhine moſt in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152468:17"/>the greateſt darkneſs, and then with thoſe fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of God here in my text, ſhew themſelves moſt zealous for the Lord, when others are moſt audacious in ſinning againſt the Lord? Tuis then doth moſt ſharply reprehend all formal and temporizing profeſſors, who, contrary to the rules of Gods moſt holy Word, contrary to the practice of ſo many of his renowned ſervants in former ages, and contrary to the irrefragable truth of the point in hand, hold it beſt and ſafeſt to ſwim with the common current, to keep themſelves on the warm ſide of the hedge, as we uſe to ſay; to do as the moſt do, though in and by ſo doing, they be utterly undone for ever: nay, and that they may not ſeem <hi>ſine ratione inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire,</hi> to be mad without reaſon, they plead Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or rather wreſt and pervert Scripture, for the defence of their wicked purpoſe; as, that of the Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Wo to him that is alone when he falleth: for he hath not another to help him up.</hi> That, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Be not righteous over-much, neither make thy ſelf over-wiſe: why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf?</hi> I, and that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> too, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22. where he ſaith, <hi>To the weak I became as weak, that I might gain the weak: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means ſave ſome.</hi> Hence it is, that they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecuted and ſhrowded from the dint of any ſuch reproof as this is; pleaſing themſelves in a cold and careleſs mediocrity in ſpiritual matters. How many have taken up that curſed Maxime, which was all the Latine that <hi>Lewis</hi> 11. King of <hi>France</hi> would have his ſon to learn, <hi>Qui neſcit aiſſimulare, neſcit vivere;</hi> he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152468:17"/>ſycophantize and diſſemble, is not in caſe to live in a Commonwealth! They can, Camelcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, turn themſelves into any colonr, accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date themſelves to any mans humour: they can, as the Planet <hi>Mercury,</hi> be good, when in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with good; and bad, when in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of bad: Weathercock like, comply with the times, let them be what they will; and ſhift ſail to the ſetting of every winde: like the <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> of whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, that they would keep the Sabbath with the Jews, and the Lords day with the Chriſtians: like men that would ſeem to be of all Religions, when in truth they were of none: like thoſe Iſraelites, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. that ſpake both <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Aſhdod;</hi> or to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> that could both bleſs and curſe: thoſe double-minded men, of whom the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks, who are <hi>inſtable in all their ways;</hi> impriſoning the truth in unrighteouſneſs. Theſe are the men who come under this firſt Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
            <p>Beloved, all that I ſhall ſay concerning theſe profligate profeſſors, that can tune their Fiddles to the Baſe of the times, reſolving to play no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what the company calls for: The Lord will ſpue ſuch Paraſites out of his mouth, as too loathſome a morſel for his ſtomack to brook or bear. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16 ſaith Jeſus Chriſt there, called <hi>the Amen, the faithful and true Witneſs, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the creation of God: Becauſe thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t luke-warm, and neither cold nor hot, I will ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi> When a man rids his ſtomack, he gets him into a corner: ſo will Almighty God rid his ſtomack of ſuch, in the dark corner
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152468:18"/>of hell. To the ſame purpoſe I may apply that, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Ah, I will eaſe me of mine adverſaries, and avenge me of mine enemies:</hi> q. d. I will caſt up this loathſom ſtuff, that lies ſo hard upon, and is ſo offenſive to my ſtomack. Which done, the devil, as a dog, ſtands ready waiting, to lick up Gods vomit. Everlaſting wo will be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all thoſe who are neither hot nor cold; in nothing ſo conſtant, as in their Unconſtancie.</p>
            <p>And thus briefly of the firſt ſort, that come under the laſh of this Reproof.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort to be here reproved, are ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and faint-hearted Chriſtians, who, with the Snail, pull in their horns for every pile of graſs; who are aſhamed of Jeſus Chriſt their Maſters Cognizance, for every light counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſt, either of diſgrace, or danger. I am to tell you, that the Lord holds all ſuch white-liver'd ſouldiers in ſuch ſpecial deteſtation, that he will not employ them ſo far as to break a pitcher or to bear a torch in his ſervice, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.3. There are three texts, amongſt others, which I thought good to commend unto the conſideration of ſuch. The one is <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38 <hi>Whoſoever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my words, in this adulterous and ſinful generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of man be aſhamed, when he cometh in the glory of his Father, with the holy angels.</hi> Chriſt our Lord foreſaw, that, as many would take up the profeſſion of the Goſpel for their credit, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and other ſiniſter and collateral reſpects; ſo, many would withdraw from it, for fear of ſhame. I, but ſaith he, Thoſe who are now ſo ſhie of me, ſo ſhie to own me, my Truths, my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152468:18"/>Service, before men, I will one day be every whit as ſhie of them, and aſhamed to own or acknowledge them before my Father and the bleſſed angels, at that day, when I ſhall make moſt ample relation, before God, angels and men, yea, all honourable mention of ſuch as were not aſhamed of me in this world; then will I be aſhamed of them, who are loth to be ſeen forward in my ſervice. The ſecond text that I ſhall preſs upon ſuch as theſe, is that of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.20, 21. <hi>For if after they have eſcaped the pollutions of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, they are again entangled therein, and overcome, the later end is worſe with them then the beginning. For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them.</hi> 'Tis better that a man never put his hand to the Plough, then after he hath done it, with <hi>Lot</hi>'s wife, to look back, through fear and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardlineſs. It were more ſafe, yea more tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and excuſable, and that not upon a few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations. But I ſhall ſtand no longer upon this firſt Uſe; onely give you the third text, and ſo proceed unto a ſecond Uſe of the Point. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>But the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and murderers, add whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolaters, and all lyers, ſhall have their part in the lake which burns with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: which is the ſecond death.</hi> Why are the <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> firſt named, before unbelievers, murderers, whoremongers? The reaſon is, becauſe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God held them worthy to be ſet in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152468:19"/>front, and to lead the Ring-dance, as it were, of ſuch wicked ones as ſhould be hurried into hell. By <hi>fearful,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Diodate</hi> in his Annotations, he intends ſuch as through carnal and baſe fear dare not to own, or at leaſt to profeſs the Truth of God, in corrupt and looſe times.</p>
            <p>And thus far of the firſt Corollary or Dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from this Point. I come now to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it ſo, <hi>That the ſervants of God muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſhew themſelves beſt in worst times?</hi> Be we then all provoked to ſet upon the practice of this moſt neceſſary, and yet much-neglected du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, labouring to ſhine forth in evil times, like that lamp, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.17. that ſhined out in the ſmoakie furnace; or like that bright ſtar, that ſhewed it ſelf in the midſt of darkneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. Oh let our piety &amp; patience appear then moſt, when impiety and violence do moſt prevail. As the colder the air, and the harder the weather, the more the fire ſcorcheth: ſo let our zeal, by an holy <hi>Antiperiſtaſis,</hi> then flame out, and break thorow all impediments, when moſt oppugned and oppoſed. Beloved, what though we ſhould finde few or none that will ſet in, or ſide with us in this important work, in this <hi>One thing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary?</hi> yea, what though all men ſhould forſake us? yet the Lord will ſtand by us, and ſtrengthen us, as he did thoſe ſweet ſouls here in my text, who <hi>feared the Lord, and thought upon his Name.</hi> Lift up therefore the hands that hang down, and the feeble knees: let us even in the looſeſt and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſt times, advance with a holy undauntedneſs of ſpirit toward that incorruptible and never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſading
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152468:19"/>crown that is reſerved for us in heaven; like fiſhes retaining their natural ſweetneſs in the ſalt ſea; like Salamanders, which live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorcht in the fire; like Oyl, that will over-top all other liquors, but not commingle with them. If we profeſs our ſelves to be ſuch as fear the Lord, let us ever hold a conſtant counter-motion to the courſe of the world, and the corruptions of the times: let us keep our conſciences good and unſpotted, as our beſt and chiefeſt treaſure.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe this is a duty of great difficulty, and very uncouth to fleſh and bloud, take along with you theſe following Rules or Directions, for your aſſiſtance. I ſhall run them over briefly, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt: Re-inforce upon your Conſciences thoſe precepts which were recited in the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Point; and withal, conſider the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and reaſonableneſs of thoſe commands. Know, that there is not any one command of God, but is <hi>holy, just, and good;</hi> had we but eyes to ſee it, and to take notice of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. ſaith the Apoſtle in that place, <hi>The law is holy, and the commandment holy, and juſt and good.</hi> Whatſoever contrariety or antipathy there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the commands of God and the hearts of men and women, it proceeds not from any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice or unreaſonableneſs in the commands, but from the corruption and depraved diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men and womens own hearts. Who will not ſay and acknowledge, that the moſt are ever the worſt? why then ſhould we go againſt common ſenſe, and univerſal experience? nay, the Scripture, which is the Word of truth and verity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152468:20"/>tells us plainly, that the way to hell is broad, and moſt beaten: <hi>the gate that leadeth to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is wide, and many enter in at it:</hi> but <hi>the way that leadeth unto life is ſtraight and narrow, and few finde it.</hi> Now who doth not judge it better, with a few, to go to heaven, then with a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to paſs down to hell? Chriſts flock hath been ever found to be a little flock, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. when the wicked on the other ſide fill the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. This the purblinde Philoſophers ſaw; and therefore they ſay, <hi>Sapiendum cum paucis;</hi> we ſhould be wiſe, though with a few. <hi>Diogenes</hi> thought he ſhould do beſt, when he did leaſt what the moſt did. <hi>Vive ut pauci,</hi> ſaith another; Live as the feweſt live. It was a brave anſwer of <hi>Liberius</hi> in the Primitive times, who, when he was urged by <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to forſake the Truth of God, and to vote for Arrianiſm, by this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>Art thou wiſer then all the world?</hi> he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honeſtly and diſcreetly replyed, <hi>The Truth is no whit prejudiced by my ſingularity and alone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſtanding out.</hi> In a word, it matters not how ſmall the number be, if godly; nor how great, if ungodly. Multitude is not much to be ſtood upon. So then, this is the firſt Direction, Lay to heart the commands of God, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and reaſonableneſs of the commands; and hereby, through mercy, you may in the firſt place be aſſiſted in the performance of this great incumbent duty. I come to a ſecond.</p>
            <p>Secondarily: If you would ſtand up for God and his Truth, in evil, corrupt, and degenerating times; then ſtudy the great Art or Leſſon of Self-denial; learn to ſay <hi>Nay</hi> to all thoſe perſons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152468:20"/>or things (though never ſo dear or delightful) that would cool thy courage for Chriſt, or take thee off from this godly practice. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.34. ſaith our Saviour there, <hi>Whoſoever will come after me, let him deny himſelf.</hi> Now there are three or four particulars which we ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our ſelves in, in this caſe. The firſt, is carnal and fleſhly Reaſon; if that ſhould perſwade us (as 'tis apt to do) to a forbearance of our holy reſolution, by the fear of what may follow: if that ſhould dictate or ſuggeſt unto us, as 'tis <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 7.16. the place before mentioned; <hi>Be not righteous over-much, neither make thy ſelf over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: why ſhouldeſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf?</hi> i.e. Be diſcreet and wary, and ſtand not ſo ſtrictly upon terms of Conſcience: why ſhouldſt thou incur needleſs danger? Stop thine ears unto this ſubtil Enchantreſs, and rather hearken to the voice of Gods Spirit in the verſe immediately following, verſ. 17. <hi>Be not over much wicked, neither be thou fooliſh: why ſhouldſt thou die before thy time?</hi> Pray obſerve the Antitheſis or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: <hi>Be not wicked over-much,</hi> ſaith he, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the former, <hi>Be not righteous over-much; neither be fooliſh,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>neither make thy ſelf over-wiſe: for why ſhouldſt thou die before thy time?</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf?</hi> This is the voice of heaven, wherewith we are to ſtop the mouth of that wiſdom which <hi>deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh.</hi> 2. If you intend to keep in with Chriſt, then deny your ſelves in your carnal friends and relations, who will be ready enough to prompt you, as <hi>Peter</hi> did once Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152468:21"/>16.22. they will be ready to bid you to be <hi>good to your ſelves,</hi> and not to run the hazard of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace or diſadvantage. Now for a counter-poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, let us conſider, that there is no friend like God, and there is no foe like unto him. <hi>Eli,</hi> you know, paid dear for diſpleaſing the Lord, to pleaſe his children, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.29, 30, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes. And it was like to have coſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his life, for forbearing to circumciſe his child, leſt he ſhould anger his wife, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Deny your ſelves in your Liberties. <hi>Micaiah</hi> though he were ſure to kiſs the Stocks, and there to be fed with the bread and water of affliction, until <hi>Ahab</hi> returned in peace, yet would he not be byaſſed for any mans pleaſure, nor vote with the reſt of <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Paraſitical Prophets, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.26, 27, 28. And</p>
            <p>Then laſt of all, deny your ſelves in your lives, (if called unto it.) What cared the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s wrath, though it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſeven times hotter then his furnace? Kill them he might poſſibly, but hurt them he could not. He that truely <hi>ſears God, and thinks upon his Name,</hi> dreads no danger, fears no colours: he will take Chriſt's croſs upon his ſhoulders, a faggot in his arms, and his life in his hand, and ſo follow Chriſt thorow thick and thin, thorow fire and water, or any thing elſe that ſtands in his way. And this is the ſecond aſſiſtant Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt is this: Let us think ſadly and ſeriouſly upon our high and heavenly calling, and labour to walk worthy of it, as the Apoſtle often exhorts us to do. Every calling hath a <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152468:21"/>a ſeemlineſs or comelineſs appertaining unto it. A Gentleman hath another manner of behaviour then a Scullion; a Prince, then a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant: ſo ſhould a Chriſtian too: a man that fears God, ſhould not behave himſelf like other men; he ſhould demean himſelf nobly, bravely, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly, worthy of God, and as becometh a Saint, a Citizen of heaven, and a Burgeſs of the new Jeruſalem; not clowniſhly, baſely, or coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 'Tis ſome ſingular thing that God looks for from his people, and that which is above vulgar and common atchievement. And therefore, to winde up all in a word, you that <hi>fear God, and think upon his Name,</hi> look to your ſelves, that you loſe not thoſe things which you have wrought, but that you receive a full reward. <hi>The ends of the world</hi> (you ſee) <hi>are come upon us;</hi> we are caſt upon the laſt and worſt times of all, even thoſe <hi>perilous times,</hi> which the Apoſtle long ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of; wherein <hi>iniquity aboundeth,</hi> and <hi>the love of many is waxen cold.</hi> How many amongſt us are fallen from the love of the Goſpel? How is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion turned with many into meer formality, and matter of diſcourſe; our ancient heat and forwardneſs, to a general coldneſs in profeſſion, lukewarmneſs in Religion, denying the power of it in our lives and converſations!</p>
            <p>Well, I ſhall ſay but little more unto you then this: That which you have already, <hi>hold fast until Christ comes;</hi> and ſeeing you know theſe things beforehand, <hi>take heed lest you alſo be pluckt away with the errour of the wicked, and fall from your own ſtedfastneſs.</hi> Beware of turbulencie of ſpirit, of deſpiſing dignities and dominion; of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152468:22"/>lawful Authority: live peaceably in the State, and in your ſeveral places: but take heed that you prove not men and women of polluted lips, by living among a people of polluted lips: learn not to ſwear, with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> by converſing with Swearers; or to curſe, with <hi>Peter,</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a while among the ruffianly companions. The worſe, the more corrupt or erroneous, yea, the leſs comfortable that any times are, the better ſhould we be, and the oftener in Gods preſence; the more religiouſly ſhould we <hi>contend for that faith which was once delivered unto the Saints;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then, with thoſe <hi>fearers of God</hi> here in my Text, ſhould we <hi>ſpeak often one to another.</hi> And thus much of this Point, taken from the copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or connexive particle, <hi>Then,</hi> in the front of the Text. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten one to another,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And thus far of the duty here performed, in reference to the firſt circumſtance of it, the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of Time, included in the connexive particle <hi>Then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now handle it in relation to its ſecond circumſtance, the circumſtance of Perſons, who they were, or what they were, that ſpake thus often one to another in thoſe corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved times: and they are deſcribed by a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble property, or <hi>periphraſis:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They were ſuch as <hi>feared the Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. They were ſuch as <hi>thought upon his Name.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This day I ſhall ſpeak onely of the firſt of them, the <hi>fearers of the Lord: Then they that feared the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The fearers of the Lord,</hi> or,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152468:22"/>which is all one, <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the Spirit of God by our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet makes this the mark, note, or diſtinguiſhing character <hi>between the righteous and the wicked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not;</hi> I obſerve this Doctrine for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, namely,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That every true and faithful ſervant of God is a fearer of God.</hi> Every ſuch a one hath his heart ſeaſoned and poſſeſſed with the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall
<list>
                  <item>1. Open the Point.</item>
                  <item>2. Confirm it. And</item>
                  <item>Laſt of all, apply it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of the Doctrine, I muſt diſtinguiſh of <hi>fear.</hi> There is a threefold <hi>fear</hi> ſpoken of in Scripture:
<list>
                  <item>1. Natural.</item>
                  <item>2. Carnal.</item>
                  <item>3. Holy and ſpiritual.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſhew you the nature of each of theſe, and then tell you which of them is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Natural fear</hi> is cauſed by the apprehenſion of ſome evil imminent or at hand: 'tis ſuch an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as whereby men are ſtricken, by reaſon of ſome dangerous and hurtful evil, either real, or onely imagined: that is the definition of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fear. In it ſelf it is neither good nor evil; it was in the man Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. Chriſts fear was onely a natural paſſion, which he aſſumed and took upon him, when he took upon him our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152468:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152468:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:152468:24"/>nature. Now there are four ſpecial effects which this fear worketh upon the body.</p>
            <p>The firſt, is the quaking of the members of the body.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, is the ſhaking of the bones.</p>
            <p>The third, is the ſtanding up of the hair.</p>
            <p>The fourth, is the paleneſs or wanneſs of the countenance.</p>
            <p>The three firſt of theſe appeared upon <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz,</hi> at the appearance of his viſion, <hi>Job</hi> 4.14, 15. He trembled, his bones ſhook, and the hair of his fleſh ſtood up. This natural fear we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtly blame, becauſe every thing by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature endeavours the preſervation of it ſelf, and fears the contrary: provided it do not degenerate into the ſecond, which is carnal fear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carnal fear</hi> now is that which is carried after the creature more then after the Creator. We read of it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 51.12, 13. Or elſe 'tis the dread of the Creator as a Judge, the apprehenſion of his ſevere wrath and puniſhment; and not from a true hatred of ſin: and this we may call, <hi>A ſervile</hi> or <hi>ſlaviſh fear.</hi> Thus <hi>Felix</hi> feared, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. he feared that <hi>judgment to come,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned of. This fear ariſeth partly from a defect of faith in the power and providence of God; and partly, from want of holy and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual fear, which I am to ſpeak of in the third place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spiritual fear</hi> is a holy affection, awing the whole man to obey the whole will of God: it makes us loth to diſpleaſe God by ſin, by reaſon of his great goodneſs and mercy, and for the great love
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152468:24"/>which we bear unto righteouſneſs. Of this we read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>But there is forgiveneſs with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi> And again, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. — and ſhall fear the Lord and his goodneſs in the later days. This holy and filial fear is called <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> in three reſpects, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of its object, which is God, who is a ſpirit, and the Father of ſpirits. And hence 'tis that God is ſometimes expreſly called <hi>fear, Gen.</hi> 31.53. later part of the verſe: <hi>And Jacob ſware by the fear of his father Iſaac:</hi> i.e. by that God whom his father <hi>Iſaac</hi> feared: And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.11. <hi>Vow and pay unto the Lord your God; let all that be round about him bring preſents unto him that ought to be feared.</hi> In the Original, it runs thus: <hi>Bring preſents unto fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then 2. This holy fear is called <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> from the principal efficient author of it, which is the holy Spirit of God, who is ſometimes called a ſpirit of fear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2.</p>
            <p>And then 3. Spiritual, in reſpect of thoſe ſpiritual effects which it produceth or worketh in the heart of man. I ſhall name three of them very briefly.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, it doth ſpiritually enlarge the heart towards God. Fear, under a natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ſhuts and ſtraitens the heart, and makes a man leſs then he was in all his abilities; but ſpiritual fear, or fear ſpiritualized, makes a man more then he was, and better then he was; it doth exceedingly enlarge the heart toward God: and therefore you ſhall finde <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement</hi> put together, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.5. where the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152468:25"/>Prophet ſpeaking of the holy fear which ſhould follow that glory of the Church, in the abundant acceſs of the Gentiles to the Goſpel, he ſaith, <hi>Then thouſhalt ſee, and flow together, and thine heart ſhall ſear, and be enlarged, becauſe the abundance of the ſea ſhall be converted unto thee, the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſpiritual fear is a bridle to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us from ſin. An example of it you have in <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 39.9.</p>
            <p>And then thirdly, as 'tis a bridle to reſtrain us from ſin; ſo 'tis a bond to hold us to duty: it will conſtrain us unto well-doing: <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me:</hi> q. d. The more you fear me, the cloſer will you keep to me. None live ſo near God, none obey God ſo much, as they who fear him in this manner.</p>
            <p>And thus have I given you the ſorts and kinds of <hi>fear.</hi> Now the queſtion will be, Which of theſe three fears we are to underſtand in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: when we ſay, <hi>That every true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant of God is a fearer of God;</hi> why (Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) we are to underſtand, the later hath his heart ſeaſoned and poſſeſſed with the holy, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, filial and reverential fear of God.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the Explication of the Point. I come in the next place to the Confirmation of it.</p>
            <p>This Point ſhall be made good unto you three ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that the Scripture doth decipher or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterize the true ſervants of God under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fearers of God; and that not onely
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152468:25"/>here in my text, (<hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another,</hi> &amp;c.) but elſewhere. Take two or three texts more. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.2. <hi>He that walketh in his uprightneſs, feareth the Lord: but he that is perverſe in his ways, deſpiſeth him:</hi> i.e. He that is ſincere and upright in the ſervice of God, he that ſerves him truly, and with a perfect heart, is ſuch a one as feareth the Lord; the fear of the Lord is upon him, nay, he is in the fear of the Lord all the day long. So again, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. <hi>But unto you that fear my Name, ſhall the Sun of righteouſneſs ariſe with healing in his wings; and ye ſhall go forth, and grow up as calves of the ſtall. You that fear my Name,</hi> is oppoſed to the proud and wicked in the firſt verſe of the chapter: <hi>For behold, the day cometh that ſhall burn as an oven, and the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly, ſhall be ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, that it ſhall leave them neither root nor branch. Unto you,</hi> i. e. who are my ſervants. And, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.16. <hi>Then Paul ſtood up, and beckening with his hand, ſaid, Men of Iſrael, and ye that fear God, give audience.</hi> Many other Scriptures might be alleadged unto the ſame purpoſe, where to <hi>fear</hi> God, is ſet down as a circumlocution or <hi>periphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> of them that truly ſerve God. When the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt would expreſs a true ſervant of God, he expreſſeth him in this variation; <hi>He is one that feareth God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, <hi>That every true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant of God, is a fearer of God,</hi> may be proved thus; in that the ſervice of God, and the fear of God, are in Scripture conjoyned, as two inſeparable or individual companions: the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152468:26"/>Spirit of God doth often make them go hand in hand together. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Now therefore fear the Lord, and ſerve him in ſincerity, and in truth, and put away the gods which your fathers ſerved on the other ſide of the floud, and in Egypt: ſerve ye the Lord.</hi> Mark it well: <hi>fear the Lord, and ſerve him:</hi> intimating, that where there is not the fear of God, there is, there can be, no true ſervice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed unto God. Reade <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling.</hi> Fear and ſervice are here coupled together. A fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs heart, is always a graceleſs heart. <hi>Fear</hi> is that affection with which we muſt worſhip and ſerve God: <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28 <hi>Let us have grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſerve God acceptably, with reverence and godly fear.</hi> Fear, you muſt know, is a compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive word; it is more then a particular grace; it contains Faith and Love too: though <hi>perfect love caſteth out</hi> tormenting <hi>fear,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.18. yet perfect love caſts in obeying fear. When <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had offered up his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that was a work of mighty faith: but yet when God commends him for it, he doth not ſay, <hi>Now I know thou hast a great faith;</hi> but, <hi>Now I know thou fearest God,</hi> Gen. 22.12. <hi>Fear</hi> is all duty; 'tis every grace: it carries every particular duty and grace in the womb of it. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Let us hear the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the whole matter; fear God, and keep his commandments, for this is the whole duty of man;</hi> or, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in the Hebrew, <hi>This is the whole man:</hi> this is that which maketh a perfect and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plear Chriſtian, a Chriſtian indeed.</p>
            <p>But then thirdly and laſtly, as the true fear and ſervice of God are in Scripture ſometime
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152468:26"/>conjoyned, ſo are they likewiſe confounded, and taken promiſcuouſly the one for the other, as reciprocal and convertible terms; fearing of God, is worſhipping or ſerving of God. You may ſee this clearly by two texts of Scripture, conferred or compared together. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.10. ſaith Chriſt there to the devil, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> Compare this now with <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. and there you ſhall have it thus expreſt: <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſhalt ſwear by his Name.</hi> That which in the one place is <hi>worſhip,</hi> in the other is <hi>fear.</hi> So again, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9. ſaith Chriſt there, <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines, the commandments of men.</hi> Now the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> from whence that Scripture is taken, expreſſeth it thus, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. at. part: <hi>Their fear toward me is taught by the precept of men. They worſhip me according to the precepts of men,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; <hi>Their fear is taught by the precepts of men,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. So that <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi> or <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>ſervice,</hi> are identical, one and the ſame thing. And thus have you here the Point con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Scripture, <hi>That every true and faithful ſervant of God, is a fearer of God.</hi> I ſhall now anſwer an Objection, and ſo proceed unto Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
            <p>The Objection is this, briefly:</p>
            <p>How do you ſay, <hi>That the true and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, are fearers of God;</hi> or that the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God</hi> and <hi>the fear of God</hi> are coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; yea, that they are one and the ſame thing? whenas in Scripture we are required to <hi>ſerve God without fear,</hi> as namely, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74. by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152468:27"/>this text it appears, that the <hi>ſervice of God</hi> and the <hi>fear of God</hi> do not commingle, much leſs are one and the ſame thing. If our ſervice muſt be done without fear, how then do fear and ſervice go together? This is the Objection.</p>
            <p>Beloved, by way of anſwer, we muſt learn to diſtinguiſh of Fear: <hi>Qui benè diſtinguit,</hi> we ſay, <hi>benè docet:</hi> he that diſtinguiſheth well, teacheth well. There is a helliſh fear, and there is a holy fear; a ſlaviſh fear, and a ſon-like fear. The helliſh or ſlaviſh fear, is ſuch as ſlaves have of thoſe, or towards thoſe to whom they are in bondage: 'tis a reſpect they carry to thoſe in whoſe power, and under whoſe command they are: they do indeed that which is enjoyned them; but they neither love their commanders, nor take any complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or delight in that which is commanded them: what they do, they do by coaction and enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in fear of the whip. Such is the fear of God in reprobates and in wicked men: they are ſtricken with a kinde of awe of Gods great and terrible majeſtie; they do even tremble at his judgements: they do, it may be, what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, but their obedience proceedeth not out of any love to God, or out of any true affection to the ſervice. Thus <hi>Cain, Eſau, Pharaoh, Ahab, Judas,</hi> and others, feared: they had ſome appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the terrour of the Lord, and that wrung ſomething from them, in which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of themſelves they took no manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: <hi>Cain</hi> caſt down his countenance, <hi>Eſau</hi> wept, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> let the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, <hi>Ahab</hi> humbled himſelf, <hi>Judas</hi> repented, as I could ſhew you from ſeveral Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152468:27"/>But then ſecondly, there is a holy, filial, and childlike fear; and 'tis a fear to offend, ariſing out of the ſenſe and feeling of the love of God; as, when the experience I have had in mine own ſoul, of Gods merciful and gracious dealing with me, makes me to entertain a fear leſt I ſhould abuſe his love, and turn his grace into wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and do ought that might diſpleaſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie; as I ſhewed you before, in the opening of the Doctrine. And this kinde of fear may be, where is the greateſt and firmeſt, yea, the moſt reſpective love; as betwixt the father and the ſon, the husband and the wife.</p>
            <p>This diſtinction of Fear being thus premiſed, it will be eaſie to untie the knot, or to ſolve the Querie. When we are required to ſerve God without fear, we are to underſtand the foreſaid helliſh, ſervile, or ſlaviſh fear. When <hi>Zacharies</hi> meaning, in that <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. is this: whereas the face of God is naturally a terrour to us, even as the face of a Judge is to a malefactor: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our ſervices are ſo full of defects and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, as that we can have no courage to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them unto God, nor hope that he will accept them. This is the end of our Redemption, that being certainly perſwaded of the favour of God in Chriſt, and of remiſſion of ſins by him, this ſervile and ſlaviſh fear muſt be laid aſide, and we may come boldly unto the throne of grace, and comfortably aſſure our ſelves that God for Chriſts ſake will accept even our imperfect and ſcant meaſure of obedience. This ſervile fear now, and the true ſervice of God, cannot ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea, they are oppoſite and contrary one
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152468:28"/>to another. But now when I ſay in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>That the true and faithful ſervants of God are fearers of God;</hi> and that the fear and ſervice of God are joyned together: I intend, as I told you before, a holy, filial, child-like, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential fear; and with ſuch a fear every true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God fears God. The fear and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God are put together, and muſt ever go together; nay, without it we can never ſerve God truly, and as we ought to do.</p>
            <p>And thus having anſwered the Objection, I ſhould in the next place proceed unto Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Uſes of the Point ſhall be three.
<list>
                  <item>1. For Information.</item>
                  <item>2. Of Examination.</item>
                  <item>3. Of Exhortation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But the ordinary time being ſpent, I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ the proſecution of them unto the after-noon. Let this ſuffice for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>The firſt Uſe ſhall be for Information.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo, <hi>That the true and faithful ſervants of God are fearers of God?</hi> Why then it will in the firſt place follow, by way of Conſectary, That all ſuch as are void of the holy, ſpiritual, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential fear of God, are no better then grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and irreligious perſons. And hence 'tis, that in Scripture you finde this often made the Note or Character of a childe of Belial, <hi>That there is no fear of God before his eyes. Abraham</hi> looks upon <hi>Gerar,</hi> as a place or people that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all goodneſs, as a place wherein he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152468:28"/>could not be ſafe, upon this account, becauſe the fear of God was not amongſt them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.11. where he ſaith, <hi>Becauſe I thought, Surely the fear of God is not in this place: and they will ſlay me for my wifes ſake.</hi> Thus David deſcribes the whole man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.1. <hi>There is no fear of God before his eyes.</hi> They have no impediment in the way of their luſt, who have once caſt off the fear of God. As they are unready to do or ſay any thing that is good; ſo are they ready to do or ſay any thing that is evil. As they can eaſily reſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from duty, ſo have they no reſtraint upon them from iniquity. This <hi>Abraham</hi> knew, and ſo he could not think himſelf ſecure there. The profeſſion (I confeſs) of ſome wicked men, may ſay that they fear God: but their tranſgreſſions, or trade of ſin, ſaith that there is no ſuch matter. We may interpret this text of the wicked mans ſaying thus, three ways. Some ſay it with their mouthes, and are not aſhamed to utter their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt the fear of God. 2. All wicked men, yea, the moſt modeſt of them, ſay it in their hearts; they are inwardly enemies to the fear of God. And very many (in the third place) ſay it in their lives. Now all theſe, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> are wicked men: if once the fear of God be caſt off, all wickedneſs is let in: at the ſame door at which the fear of the Lord goes out, any ſin or abomination may enter. Nay, you ſhall finde yet further, that after a large enumeration of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominations found in mens hearts and lives, the Spirit of God names the want of this holy fear of God, as the mother and curſed root of them all. You may ſee this in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152468:29"/>What are not men, yea what wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt they be, when once they are deſtitute of the fear of God? Sorcerers, Adulterers, Swearers, Oppreſſors, and what not? The judge ſpoken of, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.2. is therefore termed <hi>unjuſt,</hi> becauſe he feared not God: <hi>There was in a city a judge, which feared not God:</hi> Wanting the fear of God, what ſhould keep him from injuſtice? So again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13, and the following verſes: <hi>There is none that underſtandeth, there is none that ſeeketh after God: they are all gone out of the way, they are toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become unprofitable; there is none that doth good, no not one. Their throat is an open ſepulchre, with their tongues they have uſed deceit,</hi> &amp;c. Now mark the concluſion in the 18 verſe: <hi>There is no fear of God before their eyes.</hi> This brings up the rere, as it were; as to entertain <hi>the fear of God, is the beginning of wiſdom,</hi> Prov. 1.7. The word here uſed for <hi>beginning,</hi> ſignifieth not onely the beginning, but the top, the chief, the head and higheſt perfection of a thing: now as the fear of God is both firſt and laſt, the beginning and end of holineſs; ſo to caſt off the fear of God, is the beginning and ending of all wickedneſs, the upſhot of all wickedneſs: a man that hath caſt off the fear of God, is deſperately wicked.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, Are there any people ſo barbarous, is there any perſon ſo brutiſh, that feareth not God?</p>
            <p>Beloved, I confeſs there is nothing more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, then to ſtand in awe of a Deity. Hence it is, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God,</hi> in the Greek tongue, hath his name from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>fear,</hi> as ſome derive it: and ſometime the Scripture uſeth the word <hi>fear,</hi> or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152468:29"/>terrour, for God, as you heard in the morning: and the reaſon is, becauſe of the fear that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly due unto him. But that all fear not the true God, or that they do not fear him with a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſpiritual, and filial fear, and ſo conſequently are none of his, is more then evident. I ſhall clear theſe things unto you diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All men fear not the true God, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, which they ſubſtitute and ſet up in the room, place, and ſtead of God. Some fear idols, and devils, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. ſome, the Queen of heaven, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17. Some fear diſgrace; ſo <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30. ſome, danger, and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of great ones; as <hi>Pilate,</hi> who feared, if he releaſed Chriſt according to his conſcience, <hi>Ceſar</hi> would pull his Purple over the ears, and kick him off the bench. Some fear the loſs of goods; as the rich young man, who went away ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, when he was required to ſell all that he had. Some fear the loſs of their liberty; as thoſe who forſook <hi>Paul</hi> the priſoner, and were aſhamed of his chain, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>At my firſt anſwer no man ſtood with me, but all men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook me.</hi> And then, ſome again fear the loſs of life, ſhrinking in the ſhoulder when call'd to bear the croſs of Chriſt. Thus, I ſay, men fear any thing beſides what they ſhould fear, I mean God, the proper object of this, and of our other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Well then, 'tis clear, you ſee, that all men fear not the true God, that God who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to be feared.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond is as evident. Thoſe that profeſs to fear the true God, how few of them are there to be found, who fear him in truth,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152468:30"/>who fear him with this noly, filial, and ſpiritual fear, which is the fear I now ſpeak of? If ſo, <hi>what means the bleating of the ſheep, and the lowing of the oxen which we hear?</hi> what mean the Oaths, Drunkenneſs, the Sabbath-breaking, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, the Pride, that we ſee and hear to be amongſt us? Beloved, if the true fear of God were amongſt us all, do you think that theſe vices could rule and reign amongſt us as they do? Doubtleſs they could not: theſe ſins are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent and incompatible with a true and holy fear. Alas, how little of this reverential fear of God is there in the hearts of moſt men? The Pſalmiſt, in the fore-mentioned 36 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> in the beginning of it, makes this good, both in reſpect of evil to be avoided, and of good to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: My minde gives me, ſaith he, and I am verily perſwaded, having taken ſome obſervation of the wicked mans way, that there is no fear of God in his heart: <hi>The tranſgreſſion of the wicked ſaith within my heart, that there is no fear of God before his eyes.</hi> But what is the ground of this perſwaſion? may it not be a raſh and unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cenſure that <hi>David</hi> paſſeth upon him? No, ſaith he, I will prove what I ſay, both from his thoughts, words and actions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From his Thoughts. He makes no ſcruple or conſcience at all of evil thoughts: he thinks that thoughts are free, and therefore ſuffers them to rove and wander any way: <hi>He deviſeth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief upon his bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> he formeth, frameth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triveth it inwardly in his heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I prove it from his words: ſaith <hi>David, They are ſtout againſt God,</hi> as the words of thoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152468:30"/>wicked ones before my text were: <hi>Your words have been ſtout againſt me, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then 3. From his deeds, in the later part of the fourth verſe: <hi>He ſetteth himſelf in a way that is not good: he abhorreth not evil.</hi> Leave ſome ſin perhaps he may, out of ſome politick ends and reſpects: but loath and abhor it, that he doth not.</p>
            <p>This now is the diſpoſition of all wicked men in reference to that which is evil: their very thoughts, words and actions are groſly and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably wicked; and this ſufficiently ſheweth that they have no fear of God before their eyes. And as this is true in reference to Evil, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in reſpect of that which is Good. I ſhall ſhew you this in a word, and ſo conclude this firſt Uſe.</p>
            <p>A wicked perſon, ſaith the Prophet, hath no fear of God before his eyes, becauſe <hi>he hath left off to do good,</hi> verſ. 3. later part of it. With theſe miſcreants before my text, he accounts it a courſe of no benefit or profit, to be religious: he ſees it not needful to ſeek to the Lord: he <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth prayer,</hi> ſaith <hi>Eliphaz,</hi> Job 15.4. What <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaz</hi> here ſpeaks, is true of a wicked man in <hi>theſi,</hi> a wicked man reſtrains or leſſens prayer; but not true in <hi>hypotheſi,</hi> as referr'd to <hi>Job:</hi> this was true in the Doctrine, but not in the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Now, Beloved, to caſt off Prayer, is to caſt off God: he that lives without prayer in the world, lives without the fear of God in the world: and hence you finde <hi>the heathen that know not God,</hi> and <hi>the families that call not upon his Name,</hi> joyned together, or indeed rather the ſame, <hi>Jer.</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152468:31"/>10.25. Much more might be ſaid in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: but what is already ſpoken, is enough to make this manifeſt, namely, That all men do not fear God in a holy and ſpiritual manner; and ſo by direct conſequence, are no true ſervants of God, but graceleſs and irreligious perſons.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall ſerve for the firſt Uſe, the Uſe of Information. I now proceed unto the ſecond.</p>
            <p>And that ſhall be an Uſe of Examination.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo, as you have heard in the Doctrine, <hi>That every true and faithful ſervant of God, is a fearer of God?</hi> Let us then call our ſelves to an account, and ſo learn to ſettle the ſoundneſs of our gracious eſtate, by ſecuring this unto our own ſouls, That we are men and women truly fearing God. Without this, we can never aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our own hearts that we are the true and faithful ſervants of God: unleſs we be fearers of God, we cannot ſay that we are the ſervants of God.</p>
            <p>But then you will ſay, How may I come to know whether or no, with thoſe ſweet and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſouls in the text, I am a man or a woman truly fearing God?</p>
            <p>Now to the end that I may give you ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this Querie, I ſhall lay down ſome Notes of Trial, whereby I deſire all that hear me this evening to prove their preſent eſtate and condition, whether they have this holy fear of God implanted in their hearts yea or not.</p>
            <p>The way that I ſhall preſcribe for Trial, ſhall be taken from the concomitants, or, if you will, from the effects, or that lovely train of heavenly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152468:31"/>graces that guard and attend the true fear of God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place then, where there is the holy fear of God, there is purity and holineſs: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.9. ſaith <hi>David</hi> there, <hi>The fear of the Lord is clean:</hi> clean, nor onely formally, and in it ſelf; but effectively; <hi>i.e.</hi> it makes the man clean, and keeps him clean: it ſtands as a Porter at the door of the ſoul. If you ſhould come to a Princes Court, and ſee a great croud about the door, you would ſay, The Porter is there, he ſtops and examines them: if at another time you ſee all going in as faſt as they pleaſe, you will ſay, The Porter is out of the way. Thus where the true fear of the Lord is, all is kept within compaſs: we examine what goes into our hearts, and what comes out: 'tis as it were an armed man, or Centinel, at the gate, which queſtions all, and ſtops every one from entring, that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: it ſtands as a watch-man on the tower, and looks every way, to ſee what is coming unto the ſoul. But more particularly, this holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential fear of God cleanſeth
<list>
                  <item>1. The Head.</item>
                  <item>2. The Heart.</item>
                  <item>3. The Life or Converſation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A word or two of each of theſe. I ſhall not hold you longer then the ordinary time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It cleanſeth the Head, the Judgment, the Underſtanding, and intellectual part of man; and therefore ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> of true, ſpiritual, and ſaving wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: it will, according to the meaſure of it, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152468:32"/>the miſts and fogs of Errour that cloud the Underſtanding. And what is the reaſon of it? the Reaſon is, becauſe it is the property of this fear to make men humble: the true fear of God is an humbling grace. Now an humble man can never be an Heretick. 'Tis true, he may erre in his judgement; but 'tis but ſhewing him his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and he will quickly yeeld, and ſubſcribe to Truth: This heart-humbling Fear wo'nt ſuffer him to be contumacious or obſtinate. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.7. ſaith the Angel there, that had the everlaſting Goſpel to preach to them that dwell on the earth, <hi>Fear God, and give glory to him.</hi> Give glory to him, <hi>i.e.</hi> as ſome expound the place, Give glory to him, by abdicating and abjuring your heretical conceipts, and erroneous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A man that hath his heart poſſeſs'd with the lively fear of God, will not, cannot ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſiſt in any Errour: ſuch a man will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced and taken off, when other men are wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto their own opinions. The fear of God hath an excellent influence this way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cleanſeth the heart too: it preſerves the ſoul in general, and keeps it holy. O Beloved, this true and holy fear of God, is a golden bridle to the ſoul, when it would run out unto any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: it is like the banks to the ſea, which keeps in the raging waves of corruption, when they would overflow all. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.27. <hi>The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, to depart from the ſnares of death:</hi> i.e. either from ſin, which is ſpiritual death; or from damnation, which is perpetual and eternal death: the fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, to depart from both
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152468:32"/>theſe ſnares of death. Where this fear is not, there the heart is ready to joyn with every evil, and ſo to fall into the jaws of every death. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that mighty hunter, hath laid ſnares for our poor ſouls in all places. The way of this world is like <hi>the vale of Siddim,</hi> ſlimy and ſlippery, full of Lime-pits and pitfals, ſnares &amp; ſtumbling-blocks, laid on purpoſe to maim and to miſchief our ſouls: But now he that truly fears God, comes off without great hurt; he keepeth his heart with all diligence; he watcheth the very thoughts and motions of his heart: he will not ſuffer vain thoughts to lodge there, but labours to waſh it from all filthineſs, that ſo he may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect holineſs in the fear of God. This fear of God weeds hypocriſie out of the heart; pride, arrogancie, and every ſecret way of iniquity. <hi>Job</hi> was a man fearing God, and therefore he durſt not once to think luſtfully upon a maid: this was that which made him to refrain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative wickedneſs: <hi>Job</hi> 31.1.</p>
            <p>And then 3. As this holy fear of God clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Head and the Heart, ſo it cleanſeth the Hands too: it keeps the Life and Converſation pure. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.7. ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> there, <hi>Fear the Lord, and depart from evil.</hi> The fear of the Lord is to depart from evil: that, Beloved, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of the fear of God. Eſchewing of evil is not onely put as an effect of the fear of God, as when 'tis ſaid of <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 1.1. <hi>that man was perfect and upright, and one that feared God, and eſchewed evil;</hi> but it is put, I ſay, in the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition it ſelf of the fear of God: 'tis the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this fear of God, to depart from evil;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152468:33"/>not onely from habitual and inward, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from outward and practical evil; from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as well as from private and ſecret evil. See what <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſaith in his charge unto his Judges, when they were going their Circuit, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7. <hi>Wherefore now, let the fear of the Lord be upon you: take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</hi> q. d. This fear of God, if it be upon you, if it be radicated and rooted in your hearts, will teach you to forbear Bribery and iniquity with your hands. It was the fear of God, Beloved, that reined in <hi>Joſeph</hi> from condeſcending to the wicked motion of his wanton Miſtreſs; though he might have committed that folly, and the world have been never the wiſer.</p>
            <p>I can proceed no further at preſent, in the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of this holy fear of God. Examine your ſelves by what hath been ſaid. If, with thoſe godly ones here in my Text, you are men and women truly fearing the Lord; then this fear of God hath had this cleanſing influence upon you, and hath cleanſed your Heads, Hearts, and Hands.</p>
            <p>Secondly: As this holy fear of God cleanſeth the Head, Heart and Hand from ſin: ſo doth it no leſs frame the heart to the doing of duty; and that, 1. towards God; 2. towards men. For as you heard before, the fear of God is a very extenſive and comprehenſive grace; it includes the whole duty of man: not onely his Negative duty, what he ought not to do; but his Poſitive duty too, what he ought to do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152468:33"/>In the firſt place then, this holy fear of God frames the heart to the performance of its duty towards God. And here I ſhall inſtance onely in two duties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It perſwades the heart to believe God and his Word. The Scripture noteth this expreſly of the Patriarch <hi>Noah,</hi> Heb. 11.7. <hi>By faith Noah being warned of God, of things not ſeen as yet, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with fear prepared an ark,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Moved with fear:</hi> what is that? <hi>i. e.</hi> with a reverent fear of that God that ſpake unto him: <hi>Noah</hi>'s heart being touched with the true fear of God, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God, even in thoſe things which were not as yet ſeen: he believed thoſe forewarnings of God concerning the judgment he purpoſed to bring upon the world; and accordingly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Ark, whereby he ſaved his houſhold, and condemned the wicked world. Thus the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clites, poſſeſt with this filial fear, believed God and his ſervant <hi>Moſes.</hi> You may ſee this clearly, <hi>Ezod.</hi> 14.31. <hi>And the people feared the Lord, and believed the Lord, and his ſervant Moſes.</hi> Pray obſerve it well: <hi>the people feared the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. As Faith may be and is the ground of holy Fear: ſo holy Fear may ſometimes draw forth acts of Faith; it will make a man tremble as much at the Threats of his Word, as at the Strokes of his Hand.</p>
            <p>And then 2. As it frames the heart to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of God and his Word: ſo likewiſe to an obeying of God and his Word; the holy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his revealed will. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.17, 18. ſaith <hi>David</hi> there, <hi>But the mercy of the Lord is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152468:34"/>from everlaſting to everlaſting upon them that fear him; and his righteouſneſs unto childrens children: to ſuch as keep his covenant, and to thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his commandments to do them.</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, you ſee, them that fear God, to be ſuch as keep his Covenant, and remember his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments to do them. A ſoul truly fearing God, is afraid to diſobey God: his heart, with <hi>David</hi>'s, will ſtand in awe of Gods Word. And hence 'tis, that in Scripture ſometimes you finde the fearing of God, and keeping of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; ſometimes, fearing God, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſs, joyned together. The former you may ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63 <hi>I am a companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy precepts. Of them that fear thee, and keep thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts:</hi> a man cannot fear God, but he muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his precepts. So again, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter; Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this is the whole duty of man.</hi> The connexion of theſe two<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhews us, that the fear of God is a principle of obedience; they that fear him, will keep his commandments: yea, they do ſo in an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical way: though they cannot attain unto, yet they wiſh well to exact and accurate obedience. The later you ſhall finde, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.35. <hi>But in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very nation, he that feareth him, and worketh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is accepted with him.</hi> A man fearing God, will be active and doing; he will be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſs, and that which is good.</p>
            <p>And thus have you briefly heard, to what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duties this Fear frames the heart towards God. I am to ſhew you, in the next place, how
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152468:34"/>and in what duties it draws the heart in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Man. The Fear of God hath a double bond in it: a bond of Obedience to God, and a bond of Love to Men.</p>
            <p>Well then, in the firſt place, the true fear of God is ever joyned with love unto our brethren. The Apoſtle puts ſo much of Religion, or of the fear of God (for they are both one) in the love to our brethren, as that in one place he makes it all Religion, yea, the very definition of the fear of God. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure religion, and undefiled before God, and the Father, is this, To viſit the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the world.</hi> This is <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>pure Religion:</hi> i.e. This is a great branch and part of Religion; 'tis a ſpecial fruit which ſprings from that goodly tree, The Fear of God. Now to viſit the fatherleſs, Beloved, is more then to look upon them, and to ask them how they do: to viſit them, is to help and ſuccour them: it's like that viſit, in its proportion, which Chriſt made unto the diſtreſſed world, <hi>Luke</hi> 1 68. where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael: for he hath viſited and redeemed his people:</hi> or, <hi>he viſited his people, to redeem them.</hi> And then the <hi>fatherleſs</hi> to whoſe viſit Religion and the fear of God leads us, are not onely poor children and orphans, whoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents are lately dead, and they not able to ſhift for themſelves; but the fatherleſs are all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted who want our help or patronage: every helpleſs and comfortleſs ſoul is an orphan with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out parents, and as a widow without a husband: and to relieve ſuch, is <hi>pure Religion:</hi> herein ſtandeth much of the fear of God. Job 6.14.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152468:35"/>
               <hi>To him that is afflicted, pity ſhould be ſhewed from his friend; but he forſaketh the fear of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> I finde a variety of reading upon theſe words: but this one reading, to my minde, gives the ſenſe moſt fair and eaſie: <hi>To him that is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>otherwiſe he forſakes the fear of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty:</hi> whereas our Tranſlation ſaith, <hi>But he forſaketh;</hi> this ſaith, <hi>Otherwiſe he forſaketh the fear of the Almighty.</hi> i.e. If a man do not ſhew love and pity to his afflicted brother, that man ſheweth that he hath forſaken the fear of the Almighty. As love to God, ſo the fear of God is made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding viſible in love to men. As <hi>he that ſaith he loves God, and hateth his brother, is a lyer,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.20. ſo, he that ſaith he feareth God, and hateth his brother, is a lyer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. What cares <hi>Nabal</hi> the churl, though <hi>David</hi> die at his door, as long as he may ſit warm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, eating the fat, and drinking the ſweet? <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> hath Logick to conclude for himſelf, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.11. <hi>Shall I then take my bread, and my water, and my fleſh that I have killed for my ſhearers, and give it unto men whom I know not whence they be?</hi> But the fear of God would have taught the fool more wit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The true fear of God, as it will teach a man to love his brother; ſo it will teach him not to vex, oppreſs, or brew beat his brother. An inſtance of this you have in God-ſearing <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> ſee what he tells his bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.18. <hi>This do, and live: for I fea God:</hi> q. d. I intend you to hurt, although you are fallen into my hands: I fear God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is your ſecurity: it ſtands not with the fear of God, which hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152468:35"/>taken up my heart, to oppreſs or wrong you: I fear God, and therefore dare not to do you any hurt: I fear the true God, the proper object of fear; and therefore you need not to doubt of fair dealing. To the ſame purpoſe, ſee what <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaith to thoſe mercileſs Uſurious Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, that had exacted upon their brethren, <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>Alſo I ſaid, It is not good that ye do: ought ye not to walk in the fear of our God, becauſe of the reproach of the heathen our enemies? I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and my brethren, and my ſervants, might exact of them money, and corn: I pray let us leave off this uſury.</hi> q. d. Oppreſſion and the fear of God will not ſtand together: it's an argument that there is little or no fear of God in their hearts, who do oppreſs others. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.17. <hi>Ye ſhall not therefore oppreſs one another; but thou ſhalt fear thy God: for I am the Lord your God.</hi> Whereby is fully intimated, that if they oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, they did not fear God. And when <hi>Amalek</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll upon the Jews, and ſmote ſome of them paſſing thorow his Country, it is ſaid, <hi>He feared not God,</hi> Deut. 25.17, 18. This evil is an unnatural evil; and ſo can never conſiſt with the true fear of God.</p>
            <p>And then 3. This fear of God will teach men to honour and obey lawful Authority: and therefore you ſhall finde them both joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. later part of the verſe: <hi>Fear God. Honour the king.</hi> q d. Where there is not due honour and obedience yeelded to lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, there is no true fear of God. Nay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, I may adde, that this fear of God will teach a man how to carry and behave himſelf in every eſtate and condition whatſoever. Nay,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152468:36"/>it will teach all eſtates and degrees whatſoever: it will teach the Poor how to carry themſelves in adverſity, and the Rich how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in proſperity: the Poor it will teach to be contented with their eſtate and condition, as knowing that of <hi>Solomon, Pr.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Better is little with the fear of the Lord, then great treaſure, and trouble therewith:</hi> it will teach him to know, that contented godlineſs is great riches. It is not the great Cage that makes the bird ſing: it is not the great eſtate that always brings inward joy, or cordial contentment. And then as it will teach the Poor contentment; ſo it will teach them not to envie the Rich, ſeeing God in his providence hath meted out unto every one the portion of his allowance; and with this condition too, that <hi>where much is given, much ſhall be required.</hi> Hence is that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.17. <hi>Let not thine heart envie ſinners, but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long. Solomon,</hi> you ſee, deſcribes this fear of the Lord, as an antidote or preſervative againſt that evil diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>And then in the laſt place, this fear of God will likewiſe teach the Rich how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in proſperity: it will teach them to behave themſelves humbly, according to that of the Wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.4. <hi>By humility, and the fear of the Lord, are riches, and honour, and life. By humility, the fear of the Lord;</hi> ſo the Original runs, without the Grammatical copulative <hi>and;</hi> to note unto us, that there is ſuch a neer affinity between humility and the fear of God, as if they were one and the very ſame thing: they ſeem to be predicated one of the other, as if they were
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152468:36"/>convertible terms. The Rich, if they fear God, will not be proud, or diſdain their brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe poor. And then as this grace will teach them to walk humbly, ſo will it teach them to walk thankfully too. You may obſerve this, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Neither ſay they in their heart, Let us now fear the Lord our God, that giveth rain, both the former and the later in his ſeaſon: he reſerveth unto us the appointed weeks of the harveſt.</hi> One would think that the Lord ſhould rather have blamed them for not ſaying, Let us <hi>praiſe</hi> the Lord our God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but Beloved, the former includes the later: he that truly fears God, will not fail to be thankful.</p>
            <p>And thus you have heard ſeveral Notes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may come to know whether or no, with theſe godly ones here in my text, you are men and women truly fearing God. I deſire now, that when you come home, you would commune with your own hearts; and compare your ſelves with, and apply your ſelves to theſe ſundry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bational Notes. And this ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken of the ſecond Uſe, the Uſe of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſhall enter upon the third, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as far in it as the ordinary time will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>And that ſhall be a Uſe of Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo, <hi>That every true and faithful ſervant of God is a fearer of God?</hi> Learn we then hence theſe two duties: Firſt, to get the true fear of God; and then ſecondly, to grow up in this grace more and more.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe.</p>
            <p>Let every one of us labour to have our hearts
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152468:37"/>ſeaſoned and poſſeſſed with this grace, in the words of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7 <hi>Wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed, and do it: for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</hi> Give we all diligence for the attainment of this grace. Now for the better performance of this duty, I ſhall firſt lay down ſome Motives for your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; ſecondly, preſcribe ſome Means for your aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The Motives ſhall be five or ſix; all which I ſhall run over with as much convenient brevity as may be.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis but juſt, equal, and reaſonable, that we ſhould fear the Lord our God; ſeeing he hath ſo frequently commanded it, and ſo often in his Word called upon us for it. Beſides what texts have formerly in this diſcourſe been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged to this purpoſe, let me at preſent, for your encouragement, commend unto you two or three more. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.59. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.5. Obſerve well what Chriſt ſaith there: <hi>But I will forewarn you whom you ſhall fear: Fear him, which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into hell; yea, I ſay unto you, Fear him.</hi> He commands this fear twice, you ſee, in one verſe. Nay, as this fear is enjoyned, ſo doth it of right appertain to God; 'tis his due, as he is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the ſole and onely object of it. <hi>Job</hi> 25.2. <hi>Dominion and fear are with him:</hi> i.e. they are with the Lord; or, they are the Lord. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.11. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.7. So that you ſee 'tis an act of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to fear God. When we have done the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that we can this way, we have done but our duty.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152468:37"/>2. As this duty is juſt and reaſonable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, ſo 'tis a grace needful and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for us. This is that grace which enableth us unto all Chriſtian duties: it frames the heart, as you heard before, both to the ſhunning of vice, as alſo to the embracing of vertue. 'Tis <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdom,</hi> and the inſtruction of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: 'tis a <hi>fountain of life:</hi> without it, we can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther begin or end any ſpiritual work: 'tis the beginning of all, and the end of all: 'tis <hi>totus homo,</hi> all of man: without it, there can be no compleatneſs in Chriſtianity; and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. that we muſt <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> The heathen Sages, as <hi>Seneca, Socrates,</hi> and others, they were wiſe men in their generation, they had many excellent and lovely gifts: but failing of this, coming ſhort of the true fear of God, all the other did them no good: they found out indeed many excellent things, but they miſſed of this Pearl of great price. That wiſh of the Lord is very obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. <hi>Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments always, that it might be well with them, and with their children for ever.</hi> Intimating thus much, that if their hearts were once ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this holy fear, then they would be able to do his will, and to obſerve his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. Without this fear of God, we ſhall never be able to keep one of the commands of God. So that, you ſee, 'tis needful to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choation, Continuation, and Conſummation of of grace: 'tis the beginning, middle, and end of true ſpiritual wiſdom.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152468:38"/>3. As this holy fear of God is needful for us, ſo 'tis gainful to us, and profitable for us too. 'Tis true, the profane miſcreants above my text, blaſphemed to the contrary, verſ. 14. <hi>Ye have ſaid, It is vain to ſerve God; and what profit is it, that we have kept his ordinance, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of hoſts?</hi> I, but the godly in my text were of another minde. What the Apoſtle ſpeaks of godlineſs, is as true of this holy fear of God; for why? they are the ſame indiſtinct thing: now, ſaith he, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Godlineſs is profitable unto all things, having promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> This we may verifie and truly ſay of the fear of God, <hi>It hath the promiſe of this life,</hi> &amp;c. 1. Of this life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.23. <hi>The fear of the Lord tendeth to life; and he that hath it, ſhall abide ſatisfied: he ſhall not be viſited with evil.</hi> Security from evil in general, is promiſed to them that fear God: they ſhall be delivered from the hurt of it, though not always, I confeſs, from the ſmart of it. They ſhall be delivered from the evil of ſin; for why? as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.13. the former part of the verſe: <hi>The fear of the Lord is to hate evil.</hi> They ſhall be delivered from the evil of pain and ſorrow too: to which purpoſe tends ſuch texts as this; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.5, 6, 7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not be afraid for the terrour by night: nor for the arrow that flieth by day: nor for the pestilence that walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in darkneſs; nor for the deſtruction that waſteth at noon-day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand: but it ſhall not come night thee.</hi> So again, verſ. 10, 11, 12, 13. Nay, they that fear the Lord ſhall not onely be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152468:38"/>out of all evil; but they, I, and theirs too, ſhall be made partakers of all good: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12. ſaith the Preacher there, <hi>Though a ſinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged; yet ſurely I know that it ſhall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him.</hi> God will be good to his Iſrael, even to them that are of a pure heart. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.4. <hi>By humility, and the fear of the Lord, are riches, and honour, and life.</hi> The fear of the Lord, you ſee, doth not want its preſent reward of riches, honour, and life. One would think this were enough to provoke any man to turn ſpiritual purchaſer. I, but the Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this reward yet further, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9, 10. <hi>Oh fear the Lord, ye his ſaints: for there is no want to them that fear him. The young lions do lack, and ſuffer hunger: but they that ſeek the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</hi> I, but what ſhall our poor children do when we are gone? may ſome ſay well enough: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.25. ſaith <hi>David</hi> there, <hi>I have been young, and now am old: yet have I not ſeen the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging their bread.</hi> Such a thing may fall out; but 'tis rarely ſeen: <hi>David</hi> in all his experience never obſerved it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1, 2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: his ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth; the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the upright ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> Many texts we have to this very purpoſe. And then as the fear of God hath the promiſe of temporal, ſo hath it alſo the promiſe of ſpiritual and eternal good things: The Lord himſelf will undertake to teach ſuch a man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12. He revealeth his ſecrets to him, verſ. 14. He will guide them
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152468:39"/>with his counſel here, and afterward receive them to glory, as 'tis, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24. <hi>Surely Gods ſalvation is nigh them that fear him,</hi> elſewhere in the Pſalm. Read <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.5. <hi>My covenant was with him of life and peace, and I gave them to him, for the fear wherewith he ſeared me, and was afraid before my Name:</hi> i. e. with <hi>Levi,</hi> as appears in the former verſe. Thus, Beloved, ſhall the man be bleſſed that feareth the Lord. So that look which way you will, upward or downward, you ſhall finde, that this holy fear of God is every way profitable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This grace is exceeding acceptable and pleaſing unto God: 'tis delightful unto his ſoul; 'tis very contentful unto him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11. <hi>The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him; in them that hope in his mercy.</hi> Pray mark it, the word <hi>ratſah</hi> in the Hebrew, is rendered <hi>vehementer re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aliqua delectari,</hi> to be vehemently delighted in a thing. God is vehemently pleaſed or delighted in them that fear him. Let a mans ſervices and duties be outwardly never ſo ſpecious or coſtly, without this they are unacceptable to God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. <hi>To this man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a contrite ſpirit, and tremble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h at my word:</hi> q. d. To him that feareth my Name, to him will I have a gracious aſpect; and as to him, ſo to his ſervices too: but now in verſ. 3. becauſe his fear was not in their hearts, therefore he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts none of their works. And ſo again, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of your ſacrifices to me, ſaith the Lord? I am full of burnt offerings,</hi> &amp;c. Why, what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Why, my fear is not in your hearts; and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152468:39"/>hence 'tis that there is ſo much cruelty in your hands; your hands are full of bloud. Oh Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, this holy fear of God is that which gives grace and vertue to all other duties and graces whatſoever: to walk in the fear of God, is to walk before the Lord in all well pleaſing. I might enlarge very far upon every one of theſe particulars; but then, having many other things to ſpeak, I ſhould hold you too long.</p>
            <p>Well then, in the fifth place, this grace, as 'tis profitable to us, ſo 'tis honourable unto us too: you may ſee this in the text; theſe fearers of the Lord <hi>ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord, in the day that I make up my jewels:</hi> q. d. I will treaſure and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet them up among my chiefeſt jewels: I will honour them, and preciouſly eſteem and account of them, <hi>in die quo confecturus ſum peculium,</hi> in the day that I make up my peculiar treaſure, my moſt precious ſubſtance; my ſilver, and my gold, and my gems; ſo ſome read it. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which avouch God for their God, to fear him, to walk in his ways, and to keep his ſtatutes; he avoucheth them for his people, high above all nations, in praiſe, in name, and in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. You may ſee this, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.18, 19. See yet further, what God tells his Church, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.4. So again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.30. To fear God, is the crown of a woman; this is that which makes her beautiful indeed, <hi>all glorious within:</hi> I, and it makes her honourable too; <hi>ſhe ſhall be praiſed;</hi> ſhe ſhall live and die with honour. God hath left this upon record, to the everlaſting honour of <hi>Abraham, Job</hi> and others of his ſervants, that they were men <hi>fearing God.</hi> How did God even
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152468:40"/>boaſt himſelf of <hi>Job,</hi> I, and that to the devils face! <hi>Job</hi> 2.3. This was the character that God gave of him in the former Chapter: I, but now he goeth on, and ſuperaddes this unto his honour, <hi>Still he holdeth faſt his integrity.</hi> As 'tis uſual with Kings and great men of the world, for great ſervices done them, eſpecially in wars and battels, to make additions to their Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to give ſome new Motto's, or put ſome new Devices in the Coat-armour of thoſe who ſerve them: thus doth God here deal with <hi>Job;</hi> and <hi>this honour</hi> (Beloved) <hi>have all Gods Saints,</hi> all that fear his Name.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And then laſt of all, as this grace is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſo 'tis comfortable unto us: and hence 'tis, that you finde it joyned with joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. where 'tis ſaid of the Primitive Chriſtians, <hi>Then had the churches reſt thorowout all Judea, and Galilee, and Samaria, and were edified; and walking in the fear of the Lord, and in the comfort of the holy Ghoſt, were multiplied.</hi> This holy fear will free our hearts from all baſe and carnal fears. Carnal fear vaniſheth out of the ſight of holy fear, as leſſer lights do before the Sun. This holy fear fills the heart with ſtrong confidence and conſolation, making the man in whom 'tis, to hold up his head in the greateſt hurly-burly, and to walk about the world as a conquerour, void of all fear, either what men or devils can do unto him. Hence is that of holy <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 3.6. and again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1, 2, 3. There is no peace or comfort to the wicked; this is the portion of them, and onely of them, that fear the Lord. The ready way to live com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152468:40"/>is to live in the fear of God: that man, and that woman, ſhall have comfort; comfort in life, comfort in death, comfort in every eſtate and condition whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And thus, Beloved, have you heard ſeveral Motives why you ſhould ſet your ſelves in all good earneſt, for the obtaining of this grace of holy fear. In the next place, I ſhall ſhew you what Means you are to improve and make uſe of to the procuring of this grace; and that ſhall be onely one in general, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſerious Meditation. There are three or four particulars, which I muſt deſire of you (that are yet without the fear of God) to meditate upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reflect upon your ſelves, and conſider how miſerable your condition is: wanting this holy fear of God, I muſt tell you (and you muſt bear with me in it) that you are void and deſtitute of grace; you have not one grace, not one piece of a grace, or ſpark of grace in you. As where this fear of God is, there is every grace: ſo, where this is wanting, there is no grace. You are, as was ſaid in the Uſe of Information, graceleſs and irreligious perſons, having not the fear of God before your eyes: your heads, hearts and hands muſt needs be full fraught with ſin: there can be nothing but wickedneſs in you, and wickedneſs iſſuing from you: and believe it, unleſs God ſhew you the more mercy, and put his fear into your hearts before you die, you muſt expect, for indeed, nothing elſe can be expected, but all the miſeries, torments and tortures; which are the juſt reward of all ſuch graceleſs perſons, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane wretches, as want this holy fear. From all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152468:41"/>which you are utterly unable to free your ſelves. You will be able neither to abide it, no, nor yet to avoid it. And this is your very condition, if there be any truth in this Book of God here in my hand. I could out of this Book lay out your eſtate into ſeveral branches; your preſent and future miſerable eſtate. I profeſs unto you in the preſence of God, a man would not be in your caſe for a million of worlds, if there were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and this you your ſelves would confeſs, if God ſhould ever ſeaſon your hearts with his fear. But I won't at preſent trouble you with particulars. Do but go a little part from your families when you come home, and ſet your hearts upon the meditation of what hath been ſpoken unto you in general, as to your conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being without the fear of God; and this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cogitation or meditation upon your preſent caſe, may be a means (if God will but bleſs it to any of you) to pull you out of it, and of your procurement of this grace.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, as you are to reflect upon your ſelves, ſo likewiſe ſhould you meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God: let your thoughts be buſied about him; and conſider how he is, 1. Repreſented unto you in his Word: 2. How he ſtands deſcribed in his works.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, it may be, What is ſpoken of God in his Word, that may perſwade our hearts to fear his Name?</p>
            <p>Friends, there are divers things recorded of God in this Book, that ſhould prevail with you to fear before him.</p>
            <p>As firſt of all, he is tranſcendent, ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152468:41"/>and ſurpaſſing in majeſty and glory. And hence 'tis, that the Pſalmiſt infers a neceſſity of his fear, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.4. ſaith <hi>Aſaph</hi> there, <hi>Thou art more glorious and excellent then the mountains of prey:</hi> or, <hi>the mountains of triumph,</hi> (as 'tis in the Hebrew) <hi>i e</hi> the kingdoms of this world, which tear, ſpoil, and prey upon one another, like wilde beaſts: or more particularly, the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> with their goodly Monarchy: Thou art more illuſtrious, glorious, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, then all theſe. What then? ſee verſe 7. <hi>Thou, even thou, art to be feared.</hi> And again, verſe 11. <hi>Vow, and pay unto the Lord your God; let all that be round about him, bring preſents unto him that ought to be feared.</hi> Let you hearts then, in the firſt place, ſtand in a holy awe of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his great, glorious, and terrible Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider God as armed with infinite power and might: the Word beſpeaks him able to reward you, if you do fear him; and able to puniſh you, if you fear him not. Servants, you know, fear their maſters, becauſe they have power over their fleſh, over their bodies: I, but God hath power not onely over your bodies, but over your ſouls too; and therefore you ſhould fear him. You have this inference to the fear of God implied, if not expreſſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. God is ſaid to be able to conſume your body and ſoul in hell-fire; Oh therefore fear him, upon this conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider God as Omnipreſent and Omniſcient, as one that beholds and takes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all that we think, ſpeak, or do. <hi>Prov.</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:152468:42"/>5.21. <hi>For the ways of man are before the eyes of the Lord; he pondereth all his goings.</hi> God is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as one ſaith, all eye: <hi>to him all things are naked and open,</hi> Heb. 4.13. Pſal. 139.8, 9, 10. and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.27. &amp; 29 23. It was this very meditation, that kept <hi>Joſeph</hi> in a holy fear of ſinning againſt God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, conſider God too as infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſt, and ſingularly careful to puniſh ſin: and this may be a means to beget this holy fear of God in your hearts: who would not fear before this juſt and impartial God! See to this purpoſe, that ſweet ſong of the triumphant Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Nay, yet a little further: if you would have your hearts ſeaſoned with the holy fear of God, conſider him as he is preſented to you in his works: his hanging the heavy and maſſie body of the earth upon nothing: <hi>Job</hi> 26.7 his ſetting bounds to the proud waves of the ſea. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereto ſhall you come, and no further.</hi> Upon this account would the Pſalmiſt have us to fear God. You may reade it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Turn your thoughts upon thoſe particular judgements God hath executed upon others for our warning and caution. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.120. ſaith the Prophet there, <hi>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee: I am afraid of thy judgements.</hi> When one childe is whipt in a School, the reſt will tremble. Thus ſhould it be with you, when you ſee others puniſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is the ſecond particular medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which may ſerve as a means to bring you unto this holy fear, which I have ſo much ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. I come to the third and laſt; and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152468:42"/>with this I ſhall conclude this preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All you that are yet void of this holy fear of God, meditate, in the third place, upon the general judgement, and the unconceivable ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of that laſt and dreadful day, when (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>the heavens ſhall paſs away with a great noiſe, and the element ſhall melt with fervent heat; the earth alſo, with the works that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhall be burnt up.</hi> Knowing the terrour of the Lord in that day, I do earneſtly perſwade you to fear the Lord in this. <hi>Felix</hi> (though a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan) <hi>trembled,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> diſcourſed of this great day, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.23. nay, the devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhake and tremble, when they think of it; and won't you? How is it that you can think of that day, wherein the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them who know not God, and who do not fear before him? The Preacher upon this very ground, namely, becauſe then God will <hi>bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs,</hi> perſwades us to <hi>fear God:</hi> 'tis <hi>Eccleſs.</hi> 12 13, 14.</p>
            <p>And thus have I ſhewed you what means you ſhould improve for your obtainment of this holy fear. And truly, if God had revealed unto me any more excellent way, then you have already heard; I do ſo much deſire your everlaſting good, as that I ſhould not conceal it from you. Let this therefore ſuffice for the firſt branch of the Exhortation, which hath been directed to thoſe who are yet without a holy fear of God in their hearts. I ſhould proceed unto the ſecond, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152468:43"/>reflect then upon you, whoſe hearts are already ſeaſoned with this holy fear; you I ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort to grow up more and more in this grace; and lay before you likewiſe (to this end) ſome motives, and ſome means. But I ſhall put theſe things over unto the next opportunity.</p>
            <p>I proceed unto the ſecond Duty; and that ſhall be preſt and inculcated upon you whoſe hearts are already ſeaſoned with this holy fear of God. And you I do earneſtly exhort to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound and to grow up in this grace more and more. It is not enough for you to get this fear planted into you; but you muſt <hi>increaſe</hi> therein <hi>with the increaſe of God:</hi> you muſt go on, <hi>perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> And here, by way of Motive and Inducement, I ſhall refer four or five particulars unto your moſt ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Pray attend them diligently.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſhall be taken from the nature of this holy fear. The true fear of God is of a growing, of an increaſing nature. He that grows not, and goes not forward in this grace, had never yet this grace in truth Pro. 4.18. <hi>The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light that ſhineth more &amp; more unto the perfect day.</hi> A man truly fearing God, ſets forth betimes in the morning, and travels to meet the day: he proceeds from vertue to vertue, from knowledge to knowledge, from grace to grace, until he become a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once poſſeſt with this grace, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ill waxeth brighter and brighter, until at length he come to ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament, and as the ſtars in heaven for ever and ever. It may be, as the faireſt ſun may ſometimes be overcaſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152468:43"/>and darkned with clouds, ſo the piety and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a man truly fearing God, may upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be over-clouded, through violence of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temptation, and ſtrength of inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: but yet, through mercy, theſe miſts are diſpelled, and he ſhines afterward far more brightly, and runs a more ſwift and ſetled courſe in the practiſe of ſanctification. <hi>Job</hi> 17.9. <hi>The righteous alſo ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be stronger and ſtronger.</hi> The words are a circumlocution deſcribing the ſame perſon who was before called fearing God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, innocent, holy: now ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> he ſhall hold on his way, he continues his courſe, both in the holy motions of his Spirit towards God, and in the holy actings of his life towards man. And as a man fearing God is in a good eſtate, ſo ſhall he go on in a good way. The goodneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of hypocrites is as the morning cloud, and goeth away as the early dew, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.4. the wind ſcatters the morning cloud, and the riſing ſun ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hales the early dews; thus the goodneſs of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite is gone: but the goodneſs of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and of the man truly fearing God, like the goodneſs of God, of whom it is, endureth in its proportion continually: nay, ſuch a man holds on not onely in fair way, and good weather; but in ſtormy weather, and ragged ways, when his way lies among ſharp ſtones, &amp; ragged rocks, thorow briers and thorns: yea, I may ſay, when his way lies among bears and lions, he will on: The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall hold on his way: and then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>And he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and stronger.</hi> The words are a circumlocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152468:44"/>
               <hi>ut prius: he ſhall,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, be ſtronger and ſtronger:</hi> in the Hebrew it is, <hi>he ſhall adde ſtrength;</hi> he ſhall proceed from one degree or ſtep unto another. What ſtrength? why ſpiritual ſtrength, anſwerable to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7. <hi>They go from ſtrength to ſtrength:</hi> or, <hi>from company to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: i.e.</hi> from one good company to another, ſtill gathering goodneſs; and they go as the beſt go, from Duty to Duty, from Ordinance to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, from Praying to Hearing, to gather grace and ſtrength: every grace hath ſtrength; and the more grace, the more ſtrength: till we come to that which is more ſtrictly called ſtrength of grace. Nay, as it was ſaid of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, that the more the Egyptians afflicted them, the more they multiplied and grew, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.12. they multiplied in number, they grew in ſtrength and ſtature; their oppreſſion was their addition in temporals: 'tis even ſo, Beloved, with all true Iſraelites in ſpirituals, the more they are afflicted and troubled, the more they increaſe.</p>
            <p>And then as this is the nature and quality of men and women truly fearing God; ſo 'tis the nature of the true fear of God; where ever this is put into the heart, it will grow: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Scripture you ſhall finde it compared to things of a growing and increaſing nature: as, 1. to waters iſſuing out from the ſanctuary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Now this, ſaith Mr. <hi>Deodate</hi> in his Annotations, repreſents the progreſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes of grace and true fear of God in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of ſmall beginnings. 2. It is compared to a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, which proves a great
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152468:44"/>tree, <hi>Mat.</hi> 31.31, 32. They likewiſe reſemble it to the Stone that ſmote the Image, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great mountain, and filled the whole earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34, 35. So then, this is the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive to the Duty in hand: grow up in this grace of the fear of God, becauſe if true, 'tis growing. By this you may come to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you fear God with a true and lively fear: the true fear of God lives, and therefore it muſt needs grow.</p>
            <p>But then in the ſecond place, this is that which God requires and commands, yea, that which he expecteth and looketh for from our hands; namely, that we ſhould grow up more and more in this grace. Hitherto I may refer all thoſe Scriptures wherein we are exhorted to grow in grace in general, or in any particular or individual grace whatſoever; becauſe, as I have often told you in the former part of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the fear of God is an extenſive or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive word, including all and every grace. For texts referring to our growth in grace, or in the fear of God in general, reade 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Even ſo ye, foraſmuch as ye are zealous of ſpiritual gifts, ſeek that ye may excel to the edifying of the Church.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo 'tis in the Greek. 'Tis a metaphor taken from rivers of water, which the further they run, the broader they are. Seek that ye may excel in ſpiritual gifts and graces: <hi>i. e.</hi> that ye may abound in them. So 1602. 15.58. — <hi>Always abounding in the work of the Lord:</hi> In the work of the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> in all actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to your heavenly vocation, and to the true ſervice of God. See how the Apoſtle prays
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152468:45"/>for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Eph. 3.18, 19. <hi>that they may be able to comprehend with all ſaints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; and to know the love of Christ which paſſeth knowledge, that they might be filled with all the fulneſs of God.</hi> Many Wits run riot in Geometrical notions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe Moral dimenſions: and whereas Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts give us but three dimenſions of a Body; Longitude, Latitude, and Profundity; the love and wiſdom of God have Altitude added, which is a fourth. All theſe dimenſions ſerve onely to ſhew the immenſity both of the love and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Take this onely in paſſage; and ſo we might that expreſſion too, <hi>To know the love of God which paſſeth knowledge:</hi> the meaning is, to know ſo much of it as is knowable: the love of God is paſt the knowledge not onely of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but of Grace; becauſe 'tis infinite. But this is not the thing that I urge this text for: the paſſage which is to my purpoſe, and which I would inſiſt on a little, is that in verſe 19. the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of it; <hi>That ye might be filled with the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God.</hi> Divines diſtinguiſh of a twofold ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. There is (ſay they) an univerſal fulneſs; and there is a modified or qualified fulneſs. For a creature to be univerſally ſo full as God is, is impoſſible: as he is infinite, ſo his fulneſs is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; and a finite creature is not capable or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive of any ſuch fulneſs. But now take this in a qualified or modified ſenſe, ſo we may; and 'tis ordinary to be filled with the fulneſs of God; <hi>i. e.</hi> with all fulneſs accompliſhable or attainable by us: thus we ought to be filled with the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God. We are not onely enjoyned to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152468:45"/>get ſome grace, or ſome fear of God; but 'tis our bounden duty to aſpire to, and endeavour after the perfection of it, and after augmentation and growth in it. And to this end too, is that, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Christ,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>This ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken of thoſe texts which conduce to the growth in grace, or in the fear of God in general. I ſhall likewiſe briefly touch ſome texts which require an abounding in the ſeveral branches of this holy fear: as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are commanded to abound in ſaving knowledge, in true ſpiritual wiſdom, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſhould grow in faith: that which is lacking to our faith, muſt be ſupplied and made up, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.15. We ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to grow both in the aſſurance of faith, and in the exerciſe of it: in the full aſſurance of it; uſing all diligence that we might get and keep the full aſſurance of faith and hope unto the end; labouring to be eſtabliſhed, rooted, and ſoundly grounded in our particular aſſurance of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in Jeſus Chriſt, and of our own eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. And then for the exerciſe and improvement of faith; we ſhould learn every day to live by faith: let faith be upon the wing in all the occaſions and occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of our life; holding faſt our confidence, and ſtriving to be examples one to another in our faith in God; according to that, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt abound in love: <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10. bearing with, and forbearing one another; ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to enlarge our acquaintance with ſuch as fear God; and to do them good.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:152468:46"/>4. We muſt grow in mercy, and the fruits of mercy: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Therefore (as ye abound in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, in ſaith, in utterance, in knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your love to us) ſee that ye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in this grace alſo:</hi> he means, tender hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs, or bowels of compaſſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We ſhould grow in patience, meekneſs, and lowlineſs of minde: <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance contentation, heavenly mindedneſs, contempt of the world, and ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al other parts of this fear of God: but by theſe few links, you may gueſs at the whole chain, or ſeries of this grace. So then, the ſtrength of this ſecond Motive lies thus: God requires and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that we ſhould grow up more and more in the fear of his Name; he calls for it at our hands.</p>
            <p>In the third place, this is the end of our uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with, and implantation into Jeſus Chriſt, namely, that we ſhould in all things grow up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him who is the head: To which purpoſe, reade <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>But ſpeaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Chriſt: from whom the whole body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi> The importance of which words is this, namely, that we are joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and united unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ſo of his fulneſs we might all receive grace for grace: that look as an infant groweth not in one, but in every member; ſo we ſhould grow every way, in every member, and in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152468:46"/>grace appertaining unto the new creature. We muſt not walk by halfs, or obey God with reſervation; but grow up unto full holineſs. As from the natural head, ſenſe and motion floweth into the body; ſo there is internal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of grace from Chriſt the Head, into the whole myſtical body: every true believer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a vital and quickning power or virtue from Chriſt; even as a graff ſet into a ſtock, partaketh with it in the ſap and life of it. Unleſs we walk in Chriſt, we can never aſſure our ſelves that we have received Chriſt. If we ſhall ſit down and reſt in a mediocrity and ſcanty meaſure of grace, and of the fear of God; except we are ſtill on the growing hand, labouring to arrive to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, we cannot ſay that we are yet put into Chriſt. A ſoul (as one notes very well) that hath union with Chriſt, will not be like <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> ſun, which went backward; or like <hi>Joſhua's</hi> ſun, that ſtood ſtill: but like <hi>David's</hi> ſun, that great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gyant of the heavens, that like a bridegroom comes out of his chamber, and as a champion that rejoyceth to run a race. If he be joyned to Chriſt, he will joyn grace to grace, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5, 6, 7. And thus briefly of the third Motive.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, as God hath given us his Son, to the end we ſhould grow up in his fear; ſo hath be to the ſame end given us the Spirit of his Son: he hath ſent forth his Spirit into our hearts, not onely for the conveying of grace to us, but for the ſtrengthening and increaſing of grace in us. Obſerve how the Apoſtle prays for
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152468:47"/>the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Chap. 3.16. <hi>That he would grant you, according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrengthned with might by his Spirit in the inner man.</hi> This is the very office of the Spirit; he is ſent of God to this purpoſe; not onely to give us a being in grace, but to ſtrengthen us in grace: he doth not onely make us <hi>new</hi> men, but <hi>living</hi> men in Jeſus Chriſt. As the ſoul is to the body, ſo is the ſpirit to the ſoul: the Spirit furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and enableth every faculty; it enlightens the Underſtanding, it rectifies the Will, it ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth the Affections; it filleth a man with joy, fear, love, and all ſpiritual graces, which give ſtrength to the inner man; it enables us to command the winds and ſtorms of our ſinful luſts, and irregular paſſions. By the power of this Spirit, we may eject and caſt out all Satans temptations, quench all his firy darts: In a word, by the mighty energie and efficacie of this Spirit, we are enabled to every good word and work. And hence 'tis, that ſometimes the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is called <hi>The power of the moſt High,</hi> Luk. 1.35, 36. <hi>the Spirit of power</hi> too, 2 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1.7. But, why <hi>the power of the moſt High?</hi> why a <hi>ſpirit of power?</hi> Becauſe of that effectual power which the Spirit puts forth into the hearts of the elect; not onely for their converſion from ſin to grace, but for their confirmation and growth up in grace, and in this fear of God. So that now (Beloved) unleſs we do grow up in the fear of God more and more, we do as much as in us lies to fruſtrate Gods end in ſending to us his Spirit; nay, we cannot conclude that we have as yet received the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:152468:47"/>And then in the fifth and laſt place, 'tis to this end likewiſe, that God hath given to us, and continued to us his holy Ordinances. Look as the ſun and rain are given to make plants to grow; ſo the Ordinances are given to make our ſouls to grow in grace, and in this holy fear of God: more particularly, for this purpoſe it is, that God hath 1. given us his Word; and 2. his Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Word is given us to make us fruitful, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.10 11. Hence is it, that the people of God are compared to graſs, and tender herbs, which grow and flouriſh, which are fed and bring forth fruit, when watered with the rain; 'tis <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.2. A godly man, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, is <hi>like a tree planted by the rivers of water,</hi> Pſal. 1.3. he is planted and placed where Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are; and what then? <hi>he bringeth forth his fruit in his ſeaſon.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.2. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>As new-born babes, deſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that ye may grow thereby.</hi> They are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the intent and end <hi>of</hi> the Word, that do not grow <hi>by</hi> the Word. The Word is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed not onely to beget us, but alſo to make the Saints perfect. For this, you have an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent text, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. The end of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery is not onely to <hi>plant</hi> grace but to <hi>ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> grace; and therefore you ſhall finde, that when the Apoſtles had eſtabliſhed Churches, they returned to confirm the diſciples hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.21, 22.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly, as to this end God hath appointed his Word, ſo to this end likewiſe hath he inſtituted and ordained the Sacraments:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152468:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:152468:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152468:49"/>as they ſignifie, ſeal, and exhibit unto thoſe that are within the Covenant of grace, the benefits of Chriſts mediation; ſo do they confirm and ſtrengthen grace: this doth the Sacrament of Baptiſm, and this doth the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: this is the very uſe and end of them. Though indeed the Papiſts tie the grace of God inſeparably to them, and make the <hi>opus operatum</hi> matter of ſufficient virtue, and aſcribe Divine power to the very outward ſigns or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yet 'tis moſt clear and certain, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſet them up in his Church, to the end that through the co-operation of his Spirit, they might be effectual unto our ſpiritual growth; as I could ſhew you at large, were it needful.</p>
            <p>And thus have you heard what Reaſons there are, why you whoſe hearts are already ſeaſoned with the holy fear of God, ſhould grow up and abound in this grace more and more.</p>
            <p>I come in the laſt place to the means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be aſſiſted and enabled to and in the performance of this weighty, but yet incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent duty. And here I might in the firſt place urge upon you a careful, conſcionable, and faithful improvement of the foregoing Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Word and Sacraments, which, as I told you but now, were ordained to this very end and purpoſe. Did you but holily employ your ſelves in the Word and Sacraments, you that have this holy fear of God already put into your hearts, would grow up and abound in the ſame yet dayly more and more. But I ſhall enlarge no further upon them. There is one Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God more, which is very conducible
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152468:49"/>unto this great end. A Word or two of that, and ſo I ſhall conclude this ſecond Point.</p>
            <p>If you that already fear God, would thrive and proceed in this grace, why then make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and an aſſiduous uſe of faithful and fervent-prayer: deſire God, who is able to make all grace to abound, who is the <hi>finiſher,</hi> as well as the <hi>author</hi> of grace, that he would cauſe this great and comprehenſive grace to abound in you. <hi>Jam</hi> 1.5. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom, let him ask it of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not: and it ſhall be given him.</hi> This <hi>if</hi> doth not argue doubt, but onely inferreth a ſuppoſition. But why doth the Apoſtle ſpeak with a ſuppoſition? is there any man that doth not lack wiſdom? I anſwer: ſuch expreſſions do more ſtrongly aver and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm a thing; ſuch ſuppoſitions imply a conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>A ſon honoureth his father, and a ſervant his maſter. If I then be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a maſter, where is my fear?</hi> q.d. you will grant I am a father and a maſter. So here, <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom, let him ask it of God:</hi> you will grant, you all lack wiſdom. The Apoſtle, I confeſs, if you look upon the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the text, by <hi>wiſdom,</hi> intendeth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or skill to bear affliction: but yet we may alſo take it generally for every grace: <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom, i. e.</hi> if he come ſhort of, or be defective in any grace, let him ask it of God: God will have every thing to be fetched out by prayer: He is the ſountain, yea, an unexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted fountain of all grace; and therefore ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, in the ſame Chapter, verſe 17.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152468:50"/>
               <hi>Every good gift, and every perfect gift is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and cometh down from the Father of lights; with whom is no variableneſs, neither ſhadow of turning.</hi> Pray mark, <hi>Every good and every perfect gift;</hi> all ſpiritual bleſſings. 'Tis true, all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gifts come from divine bounty: but the Apoſtle here intendeth ſpecial bleſſings, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the attributes of them, in that he calls them <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect;</hi> as alſo, becauſe theſe beſt ſuit with the context: as every <hi>good,</hi> ſo every <hi>perfect</hi> gift; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as do any way conduce to our perfection; not onely initial and firſt grace, but all the progreſſes in grace; not onely the beginnings, but the gradual acceſſes of them. All theſe now are from God, from above, from heaven: and if perfection and growth in every grace is from above, why then likewiſe in this grace, wherein I am now perſwading of you to grow perfect. Thus more generally.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, as to the grace in hand, conſidering that to fear God is a ſupernatural gift; go to God for it, and pray with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 86.11. later part of the verſe: <hi>Unite my heart to fear thy Name:</hi> q. d. my heart of it ſelf is wofully divided and ſcattered up and down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lying vanities; Oh now do thou unite my heart to fear thy Name. The Septuagint ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>make my heart one;</hi> i.e. apply it onely and conſtantly to thy fear: let not my heart be divided between thy fear, and things of a lower conſideration; let it not be floating between two different ways, as if I had two hearts; but <hi>unite my heart to fear thy Name:</hi> let the fear of thy great Name, be the one onely
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152468:50"/>thing that my heart is carried after. <hi>Eliphaz</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth the neglect of this duty of prayer, as the reaſon why men caſt off this fear of God: 'tis, ſaith he, becauſe they <hi>reſtrain prayer</hi> from God, <hi>Job</hi> 15.4. He that throws up the duty of prayer, nay, he that ſhortneth or abateth prayer: for the word <hi>garang</hi> in the Hebrew, ſignifieth not onely to withdraw or keep back, but to leſſen and diminiſh. So that, I ſay, whoſoever holdeth prayer from God, or leſſeneth and abateth pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, muſt never expect to grow up in this grace. Nay, to <hi>fear</hi> God, and to <hi>ſeek</hi> God, are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in Scripture, eſpecially in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. uſed for one and the ſame thing; as you may obſerve, if you will but compare together verſe 9. and 10. of that Pſalm: <hi>this</hi> being the ready way to <hi>that.</hi> Do but ſee, in the laſt place, concerning the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſits and contents of the new Covenant, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. one clauſe of which covenant is this: <hi>I will give them one heart and one way, that they may fear me for ever: I will put my fear into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Now ſaith the Lord, verſe 37. <hi>I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael, to do it for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Beloved, have you heard the means both how you may get this holy fear of God; as alſo, how you may grow up in this grace more and more. I am loth, by reaſon the time is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſpent, to enter upon a new Point at this preſent: and therefore, in the laſt place, I ſhall adde ſome few ſigns of this growth, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to God, and to this Word of his grace.</p>
            <p>Well then, here the Queſtion will be; How
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152468:51"/>a ſoul may come to know whether or no he do thrive in this grace. And here in the firſt place, I might touch at that which was ſpoken of, both in the Motives and in the Means.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A man may know it by his conſcionable uſe of the Means and Ordinances of growing. If we will but meaſure unto God in ſincerity, in Hearing, Reading, Praying, and Receiving; no doubt but God will meaſure unto us, in the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his bleſſing. We need no more doubt whether our ſouls do grow in this grace, if we can bring conſtant affections to the means; then we need, whether the bodies of our children would grow, if they have good Nurſes, and do ſuck the breſts well. To this purpoſe tend ſuch Scriptures as theſe: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64 5 <hi>Thou meeteſt him that rejoyceth and worketh righteouſneſs, thoſe that remember thee in thy ways.</hi> Thoſe that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thee in thy ways? what is that? <hi>i.e.</hi> in thy glorious di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſations: we may refer it either to the diſpenſations of the rod, or to the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Word. Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that remember God in either of theſe ways; thoſe that make a holy uſe of either, them will God meet: <hi>Thou meeteſt thoſe that remember thee in thy ways.</hi> And what, will he ſhake them onely by the hand? no, he will ſhake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem by the heart too; he will bleſs his Ordinances to their hearts, and make them profitable and of great conſequence to their growth: as 'tis yet more fully expreſſed, <hi>Mic</hi> 2.7. later part of the verſe: <hi>Do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly?</hi> i. e. My words will do good to him; and as other good, ſo this good; it will make him grow, as you have it,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152468:51"/>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. So then, that is the firſt ſign of growth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We might diſcern this further, by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliſhing of ſin, by our diſtaſting of the world. According to the meaſures and degrees that the ſweetneſs of ſin decays and abates in us, doth grace grow and thrive in us. As there is no <hi>vacuum</hi> in Nature, ſo neither is there in grace. As corruption increaſeth, ſo this grace of the fear of God increaſeth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may know this likewiſe by our faith and confidence in God: Jer. 17.7, 8. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is: for he ſhall be as a tree planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that ſpreadeth out her roots by the river, and ſhall not ſee when heat cometh, but her leaf ſhall be green; and ſhall not be careful in the year of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yielding fruit: q d.</hi> he ſhall grow.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We may know it by our conſtancy and frequency in good works, either of piety or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: for ſaith our Saviour in this caſe, Matth. 13.12. <hi>Whoſoever hath, to him ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance: but whoſoever hath not, from him ſhall be taken away, even that he hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. We may know this likewiſe by our frequency in communion with God, by our delight in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neer to him: this is the way to grow up to an holy temple in the Lord: and in the Lords tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you may be ſure all will proſper well. I might enlarge upon theſe ſeveral ſymptomes: but the ordinary time is ſpent, and therefore a word or two more, and I have done.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth place, we may try our growth in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152468:52"/>this grace, by our humility: look as we thrive in the one, ſo do we thrive in the other. God hath promiſed not onely to give grace, but to give <hi>more</hi> grace to the humble; <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6 <hi>But he giveth more grace;</hi> or, <hi>he giveth abundance of grace.</hi> Humble perſons ſhall not onely have a being in grace, but they ſhall receive increaſes of grace.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And then laſt of all, we may know likewiſe whether we grow in this grace, by our love and affection to the godly. This love is the very <hi>bond of perfection,</hi> Col. 3 14. 'Tis not onely a means of that true and perfect union which ought to be among believers; but 'tis a means of their growth, yea, and a trial of their growth too, in any other grace.</p>
            <p>And thus have I finiſhed this Point, as alſo the firſt property or periphraſis of thoſe godly ones here in my text: they were ſuch as <hi>feared the Lord.</hi> I ſhould now proceed unto the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond they were ſuch as <hi>thought upon his Name.</hi> But of this another time.</p>
            <p>For the opening of which property, I ſhall conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. An Object.</item>
                  <item>2. An Act.</item>
                  <item>The Object: The Name of God.</item>
                  <item>The Act: Thinking upon.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A word or two of each, and ſo I ſhall come to the Obſervation.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, what are we to underſtand by the Name of God?</p>
            <p>Beloved, the Name of God, among other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications in Scripture, hath four ſpecial ones.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:152468:52"/>1. 'Tis taken for God himſelf: the name of a thing, is put for the thing named, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>Through thy Name will we tread them down that riſe up againſt us.</hi> Through thy Name, i. e. through thee: <hi>Through thee,</hi> and <hi>through thy Name,</hi> are here the very ſame. <hi>Through thy Name,</hi> here in this verſe, is added meerly exege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, to expound the meaning of <hi>through thee</hi> in the beginning of the verſe. And ſo again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.10. <hi>According to thy Name, ſo is thy praiſe unto the ends of the earth.</hi> The ſenſe of the words is this: Thou art praiſed like thy ſelf: as thou art in thy ſelf, ſo thou art, or at leaſt oughteſt to be praiſed by thy people. 'Tis fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in Scripture to put the Name for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: you have it clearly, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. <hi>The num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Names together were about an hundred and twenty:</hi> i. e. the number of perſons: ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe numbred by their names.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Name of God is in Scripture often put for the Attributes of God, and eſſential pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; for the power of God, wiſdom of God, mercy of God, juſtice of God, and the reſt; as we could eaſily ſhew you from Scripture. But I would haſten to the Points.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Name of God ſignifies his Ways, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or Worſhip: Jer. 7.12. <hi>But go ye now unto my place which was in Shiloh, where I ſet my Name at the firſt, &amp;c.</hi> What is that? <hi>i. e.</hi> where I firſt ſet up my publike worſhip. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Name of God is put for his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances &amp; Worſhip, is, becauſe as a man is known by his proper name, ſo is God known by his proper Worſhip. And hence 'tis, that often
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152468:53"/>times falſe worſhip is called the ſetting up of a ſtrange god: this is evident, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.9. and ſo elſwhere in many places. And then</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, the Name of God ſignifies that reverence, eſteem and honour which angels and men give unto God; as you know amongſt us, the report and reputation that a man hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, is a mans name; what men ſpeak of him, that is his name: ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a one, we ſay, hath a good name; ſuch a one hath an ill name: <hi>i. e.</hi> men ſpeak well or ill of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch perſons. <hi>Gen</hi> 6.4. when <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribes the gyants, he ſaith they were <hi>men of renown,</hi> in the later part of the verſ. the Hebrew is, <hi>an ſa haſhem,</hi> they were <hi>men of name:</hi> men of name, by an Hebraiſm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re men of renown. <hi>Num.</hi> 16 2.—<hi>Famous in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, men of renown:</hi> the Hebrew is, <hi>Theſe are men of name in the congregation.</hi> Becauſe the name of a man, is the opinion he hath amongſt men: as a man is eſteemed, ſo his name is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and himſelf is accepted in the world. Thus, I ſay, the Name of God is that high eſteem, thoſe honorable apprehenſions which good angels and good men have of God. Such as the thoughts and ſpeeches of men are, for the celebration of Gods glory and praiſe; ſuch is his Name in the world.</p>
            <p>Well then, now the queſtion will be, which of all theſe is intended in the text, when 'tis ſaid of theſe fearers of God, that they <hi>thought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Name.</hi> Truly I know not how to exclude any of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e four: I ſuppoſe all of them are here intended: they thought upon God, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which had any print or image of God
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152468:53"/>ſtamped upon them; his Attributes, Ways, Ordinances, Worſhip, Honour; all theſe they thought upon. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkned and heard it; and a book of remembrance was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name.</hi> And thus much of the Objects.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak a little of the Act which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about the Object, and then give you the Obſervation. The Act, you ſee, is thinking upon; <hi>And that thought upon his Name.</hi> The word in the Original is put participially, 'tis <hi>koſhebka uleko ſheba ſhemo; And for them thinking upon his Name.</hi> Now the root or verb <hi>haſhabh,</hi> whence this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple comes, is rendered by <hi>Calvin</hi> two ways: 1. To have in eſteem or great price. Theſe godly ones here in my text, were ſuch as had an high and honourable eſteem of the Name of God. This I confeſs is well expounded, and the Original is clear enough for it. But yet, in the ſecond place, 'tis as well, if not better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded according to our Tranſlation: <hi>They excogitated,</hi> or, <hi>they thought upon his Name.</hi> And becauſe this is fully as clear, if not clearer, from the Original text, as the other; I ſhall not vary from our Engliſh Tranſlation. And this word <hi>haſhabh</hi> doth not ſignifie ſimply or nakedly to <hi>think:</hi> but to ſet the head and heart on work to finde our ſomething; and carries the intention of the minde with it, as I could ſhew you, from <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.10. and other places. Well then in fine, take the meaning of the Prophet to be this: <hi>That thought upon his Name;</hi> i.e. that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152468:54"/>meditated, that buſied and bended their beſt thoughts upon God, and the things of God; upon God, and upon the things that were of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine concernment. Thus ſuccinctly and briefly, without any further enlargement. So that now having opened this property of theſe holy ones, take the Doctrine or Obſervation, thus: <q>
                  <hi>It is, and it ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and upon the things of God.</hi> All ſuch whoſe hearts are poſſeſt with the true fear of God, will be excogitating and thinking upon his Name.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall clear this from Scripture, and then come to the Grounds and Reaſons of it. Reade <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.23. <hi>The deſire of the righteous is onely good.</hi> Taavah Haddikim: <hi>The deſire of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi> or, <hi>the affection of the righteous is onely good:</hi> i. e. ſo far as he is righteous or ſpiritual: he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in the law of God after the inward man: the main ſtream of his deſires, the courſe and current of his heart, runs upon God and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Although when the fleſh gets the winde and hill of the ſpirit, all is not ſo well carried: 'tis oftentimes with a Chriſtian, as 'tis with a Ferry-man; he plies the Oar, and eyes the ſhore homeward, where he would be; yet there comes in the interim a gale of wind, that carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him back again: So, I ſay, although a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in this viatorous condition, is not ſo happy as to have his heart altogether empty of evil thoughts and deſires; yet that is the thing he ſtrives unto and breathes after: and God looks more upon the deſires of his ſervants, then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152468:54"/>their performances: every man is, in the account of God, as good as he deſires to be. So that in this ſenſe, well might <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>The deſire of the righteous is onely good.</hi> So again, <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.5. <hi>The thoughts of the righteous are right.</hi> What is that? why the meaning is, that he feeds his thoughts upon the beſt objects: and if worſe break in, as ſometimes they will, he juſtles them out again, rids the room of them, and will not ſuffer vain thoughts to take up their reſidence or lodging within him. An inſtance hereof you have in <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.113. <hi>David</hi> was a man (as you may finde thorowout the Book of the Pſalms) whoſe heart was much ſet upon God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16 8. he was a man very much buſied in holy and heavenly meditation: the ways, and words, and works of God, were the chief objects of his meditation, as you may finde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every where. Another example of this you have in the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26 8. 'Tis ſaid of theſe godly ones in my text, that <hi>they feared the Lord, and thought upon his Name:</hi> and ſaith the Church here, <hi>The deſire of our ſoul is to thy Name, and to the remembrunce of thee:</hi> i.e. to all the ſigns, gages and teſtimonialls which thou baſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us of thy grace, by thy words, works, or the like; the deſire of our ſoul is to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe: or, we deſire to remember theſe in our whole ſouls. To the ſame purpoſe is that of the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17, 18, 19, 20. So that now from all theſe Scriptures, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, it appears clearly, that <hi>it is, and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate diligently upon God, and upon the things of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152468:55"/>God.</hi> Take one text more, which ſhews that this ſhould be the practice of all that fear God: as it is, ſo it ought to be their practice; they are enjoyned to it by command, as namely, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. whence you may perceive what the objects of our thoughts ought to be: the things that we think upon, muſt be true, honeſt, juſt, pure, love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of good report; they muſt be heavenly and ſpiritual things. And ſo again, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Set your affections on things above, not on things on the earth.</hi> The word for <hi>ſet your affections,</hi> in the Greek, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and we may render it, <hi>minde</hi> or <hi>think upon</hi> ſupernatural things, upon things that are above, things that are of a heavenly and celeſtial concernment.</p>
            <p>And thus you have heard the Point made good from Scripture. I ſhall in the next place give you the grounds and reaſons of it, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed therein further, as far as time will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>Well then, in the firſt place, they that fear God, will be thinking upon his Name; their thoughts will be taken up with, and exerciſed about the things of God, becauſe they know that God knows the ſecrets of their hearts: as he that makes a Watch, knows every winding and turning in the Watch; ſo he that made our ſpirits, and is the father of our ſpirits, knows all the motions and contrivances of our ſpirits Nay, 'tis the ſole priviledge of God, to know. the thoughts: the heart is his peculiar, which none can unlock, or look into, but the moſt High: <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart, I try the reins.</hi> Now what is the heart that God
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152468:55"/>ſearcheth, or what doth God ſearch for in the heart? The heart is nothing elſe but the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of our thoughts; and God ſearcheth for nothing elſe there, but our thoughts: either ſimple, as they are in our meditations; or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, as they are in our affections. <hi>David,</hi> you ſhall finde, aſcribes this glory to the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.2. <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſearched me, and known me: thou knoweſt my down ſitting, and mine up riſing; thou underſtandeſt my thought a far off:</hi> i. e. thou knoweſt all my outward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but is that all? no, ſaith he, <hi>thou knoweſt my thoughts afar off.</hi> Our thoughts are evident to God, even before they are. Our thoughts are ſaid to be afar off, when they are not thought: yet then they are as nigh to God, as they are to us when we are thinking them, even actually preſent to him. Nay, our thoughts are as audible to God, as our words are to men: he hears the language of our ſpirits, and what our hearts ſay, when our tongues are ſilent. One man knows not the meaning of another mans thoughts while he is ſpeaking, unleſs he ſpeak his thoughts, as ſome do not: but now let the tongues of men be never ſo croſs to their hearts; and what they ſpeak, not a light to diſcover, but a ſhadow to darken their thoughts; yet God knoweth them. 'Tis ſaid of Chriſt in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.4. that <hi>he knew their thoughts;</hi> and this was an unanſwerable argument of his Divinity, or that he was God. Onely God, or as Chriſt was God man, can reach the thoughts of man: and he knows as well what is in them, as what is without. And this the godly well
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152468:56"/>know; and hence 'tis, in the firſt place, that they are ſo thoughtfull of his Name.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17, 18, 19, 20.) the godly will be thinking upon God, out of love, and ſtrength of affection to his Name. 'Tis the nature and property of love, to ſet the thoughts awork upon the thing or object be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved: according to that in the Proverb, <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſt ubi amat, non animat:</hi> the minde of a man is not where it lives, but where it loves. Pray obſerve that paſſage, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. the later part of the verſe: <hi>Thy Name is as oyntment pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth, therefore do the virgins love thee.</hi> Chriſt hath his name, both in Hebrew and Greek, from ointments; and theſe three words, <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Anointed,</hi> are all one in ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Now when the holy Ghoſt, in the mouth and miniſtery of his faithful ſervants, ſhall take of Chriſts excellencies, as it is his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, you know, to do, and hold them out to the world; when he ſhall hold up the Tapeſtry, as it were, and ſhew men the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with an <hi>ecce virum,</hi> behold the man, that one Mediator betwixt God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus; when they ſhall ſee him in his Natures, in his Offices, Works, and in the bleſſed effects of all: when his Name as oyntment is poured forth; this cannot but ſtir up wonderful love in all good ſouls: <hi>therefore do the virgins love him.</hi> By <hi>virgins,</hi> we are to underſtand the faithful, ſo called for their ſpiritual chaſtity. They love him for the odours of his good oyntments; and out of their dear love and reſpect which they bear to him, they will be continually thinking upon him:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152468:56"/>they have taſted and ſeen how good the Lord is: they have heard it not onely by the hearing of the ear, but their hearts are experimented in it: God hath ſhed abroad his love, that part of his Name, in their hearts, by the holy Ghoſt; and therefore they cannot chuſe but love him back again; and loving him, be much in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation or meditation about him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Saints are ſet upon thoughts of Gods Name, becauſe they are inſtructed and enabled thereunto by his holy Spirit, who is their dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Monitor, and ſweet inhabitant. 'Tis true, what the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves: but our ſufficiency is of God.</hi> The meaning of it is, that all our ſtrength and help lies in him: we daily finde a want in our ſelves; and God, as it pleaſeth him, lets out from his ſufficiency unto us, now a little and then a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: we are ever receiving from him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled by his Grace and Spirit to do what is done: I ſay, the Spirit diſpoſeth the heart to this holy meditation, and that two ways: 1. By enlightning the heart: 2. By enlarging the heart. But the time being paſt, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer what remains to ſome further opportunity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay, the Spirit enlightens their hearts. The firſt and primary work of the Spirit, is to beat out, as it were, new windows in the dark ſouls of men, and to put in a principle of new light thereby; giving the ſoul ſome ſigns of God, ſome ſenſe of his ſweetneſs, ſome glimpſe of his glory. And hence 'tis, that the holy Ghoſt in Scripture is ſometimes called a <hi>ſpirit of wiſdom
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152468:57"/>and underſtanding, a ſpirit of counſel and of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Iſa. 11.2. ſometimes a <hi>ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation,</hi> Eph. 1.17. ſometimes <hi>a ſpirit of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,</hi> Heb. 6.4 Now the Spirit is ſo called, from this effect which it hath upon the heart, becauſe the Spirit cauſeth a ſpiritual and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly light to ſhine about our mindes, by which, ſpiritual things are made manifeſt to the eye of our underſtanding; as by the light of the Sun, bodily things are made manifeſt to the eye of our body. <hi>The Spirit,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.) <hi>ſearcheth the deep things of God,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals them to us, and ſhews us the back parts of God, though ſomewhat obſcurely, as through a grate onely; or darkly, as through a glaſs. In this life we know but in part. And then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſpirit having poſſeſſed the heart, he enlargeth or wideneth the heart towards God, and the things of God: it enables us to capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate our thoughts to the obedience of Chriſt, to conform them to the ſeveraignty of his grace, to the rules of his Word, and the remembrance of his Name. Nay,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Spirit ſanctifieth the heart, and ſo puts it upon a continual freſh ſucceſſion of holy thoughts. The whole ſpirit, ſoul and body of a Chriſtian, is ſanctified thorowout. God writes his Law in their hearts, ſtamps his image upon the ſpirit of their mindes, makes them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the divine nature; erecteth a new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a bleſſed frame of grace: And hence have they an ability given them of holy thoughts and meditations: for as the man is, ſo will his thoughts, diſpoſitions, meditations and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152468:57"/>be. Hence is that of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.8. <hi>But the liberal deviſeth liberal things, and by liberal things ſhall he ſtand.</hi> A man of a noble, liberal, and generous ſpirit, will carry his heart out after worthy and noble things. Nay, hence is that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.35. <hi>A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart bringeth forth good things.</hi> As from the old and unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated heart proceed evil thoughts; ſo from the new and ſanctified heart, proceed holy and ſanctified thoughts, gracious conſiderations of, and holy reverend reſpects to God, and to his Name. That is the third Reaſon of the Point. <hi>It is and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the things of God:</hi> becauſe the Spirit doth to this purpoſe enlighten their underſtandings, and poſſeſſeth and ſanctifieth their hearts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But then laſt of all, <hi>it is and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and the things of God,</hi> becauſe all that truly fear God, ſtand in a marvellous neer and dear relation unto God. Neer relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you know, will minde one another. God and his ſervants are neerly related: he is their friend and father, their God and guide, their Prince and portion, their ſhield, and their exceeding great reward. Nay, Beloved, he is their all in all, the ſtay and the ſtrength of their hearts for ever: and therefore it cannot be, but their hearts muſt run much upon God, and upon the things of his kingdom. Nay, a little further: every faithful ſervant of God, every true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, hath reſigned and given up his name to God;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152468:58"/>he hath devoted himſelf to his fear. Mark what holy <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38. <hi>Stabliſh thy word unto thy ſervant, who is devoted to thy fear.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers have as it were ſworn themſelves to the ſervice of God: <hi>I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> ſaith the ſame holy <hi>David</hi> oftentimes in the Pſalms: they love the Lord with all their ſoul, with all their heart, and with all their ſtrength: and as for the Name of God, they flie unto it in any difficulty and diſtreſs, as unto a Gariſon and ſtrong Fort or Tower, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. The righteous know that the Name of God is ſo deep, that no Pyoner can undetmine it; ſo thick, that no Cannon can pierce it; ſo high, that no Ladder can ſcale it: and hither they run for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: Nay, they walk in this Name, as in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or Gallery: <hi>Mic.</hi> 4 5. <hi>We will walk in the Name of the Lord our God for ever and ever:</hi> they reſolve to walk in the Name, <hi>i. e.</hi> By the Laws, and under the view of the Lord their God, who is God of gods, and Lord of lords: they rejoyce and delight in it, as in all treaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.14 Now, brethren, ſum up all together in a word, and then you ſhall finde the force of this Argument.</p>
            <p>Can the fearers of God rejoyce in his Name, run unto it upon all occaſions, walk in it; and yet not minde it; and yet not have their hearts ſet upon it? This is impoſſible. Can they, I ſay, vouch him for their God, ſet him up for their Soveraign, converſe with him as a friend; and yet not think upon his Name? this cannot be well conceived.</p>
            <p>And thus you hear what the grounds of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152468:58"/>Point are. Let us now make ſome Uſe of it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall improve it four ways:
<list>
                  <item>1. For Inſormation.</item>
                  <item>2. For Increpation.</item>
                  <item>3. For Examination.</item>
                  <item>4. For Exhortation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In which Uſes, I ſhall proceed ſo far this day as time will permit. I begin with the firſt, the Uſe of Information.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it ſo, <hi>That it is and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and upon the things of God?</hi> Take we then hence notice, That thoſe who do not habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, daily and diligently think upon God; that make not his Attributes, Ways, Ordinances, Worſhip and Honour, the matter of their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; theſe, I ſay, are excluded out of the number and ſociety of the true fearers of God. Yea, the want of this holy and heavenly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is laid down in holy Writ, as the Badge, Cognizance, or Character of wicked men. You may finde it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. <hi>The wicked through the pride of his countenance will not ſeek after God: God is not in all his thoughts:</hi> i. e. he doth not regard or care for God; he doth not willingly medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or think of God: he maintains no correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency or communion with him in his inner man: peradventure God, like an unbidden or unwelcome gueſt, may put himſelf in his thoughs, and move in his minde; he may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his minde ſome manifeſtations of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his juſtice and holineſs; yea, of his truth, long ſuffering, and goodneſs: but this proves a trouble, and becomes a pain unto a wicked man.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152468:59"/>Wicked men neither deſire or accept acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him in any of theſe. Wicked men are weary of the preſence of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo <hi>Job</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes them, Chap. 21.14. they think it beſt for them, when God departeth. 'Tis true indeed, Saints know not how to live a comfortable day, much leſs to be happy, without him: but now wicked men know not how to live a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hour, much leſs to be happy, with him. The Church indeed ſaith to God, <hi>Leave us not,</hi> Jer. 14.8. and God ſaith to her, <hi>Wo to you when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part</hi> Hoſ. 9.12. I, but wicked men ſay to God, <hi>Depart from us;</hi> trouble us not; when ſhall we be eaſed and disburdened of his preſence? As there is nothing ſo joyous to the righteous, ſo there is nothing ſo grievous to the wicked, as to have God neer them. If they can once ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the thoughts of God, then they think they live indeed; and till then, they reckon their lives as a kinde of death. Thus the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the Gentiles before their converſion; they were ſuch as were <hi>without God in the world,</hi> Eph. 2.11, 12. All wicked and unregenerate men, with theſe Gentiles, live without God in the world. Nay, Beloved, be informed from the Doctrine in hand, That to be weary of the preſence of God, and to expel God, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Name, out of the heart, is one of the ſtrongeſt arguments, and higheſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, that a man is wicked.</p>
            <p>Onely to love and pray for the preſence of God, is the ſureſt ſign of a gracious heart; but to deſire and wiſh the abſence and departure of God, muſt needs conclude, and poſitively argue
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152468:59"/>the heart to be moſt ungracious. See what <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after; that I mar dwell in the houſe of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the days of my life, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his temple.</hi> One thing have I deſired of the Lord, and that will I ſeek after: <hi>i e.</hi> I will earneſtly purſue, I will indefatigably and unweariedly proſecute the grant or conceſſion of this deſire, <hi>that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. In theſe ſacred ſtrains of divineſt Rhetorick, was <hi>David's</hi> ſoul carried out after God: God and his Name was the one thing, the onely thing he longed for: without God, all was nothing with him: in him, he had all: his preſence was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and ſufficient for him: all companies, multitudes, throngs and crouds of men, yea, of Saints or good men, was but ſolitarineſs and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhood to him, without the preſence of God. And this was the higheſt aſcent of <hi>David's</hi> holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: well then, pray tell me, is it not the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deſcent of unholineſs, the greateſt brand and argument of wickedneſs, to be troubled at the preſence of God? Is it not a full and plenary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of a carnal minde, of a wicked man, to think it long until God be gone, to deprecate his preſence, and to urge his departure? Oh, I muſt acquaint you, that this frame of heart is the very blackneſs of helliſh darkneſs; 'tis the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs image and character of the devils perſon. Though peradventure ſuch are not poſſeſt with, yet are they under the poſſeſſion of the evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Reade that relation, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8 28, 29. It is the devils torment to be neer Chriſt, or to have
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152468:60"/>any appearance of God in him: and certainly they are neereſt the devil, they live next door to him, to whom the thought of God, and the remembrance of his Name, is a torment; or who, like thoſe <hi>Gaderenes</hi> to Chriſt, in verſe 34. of the fore-named Chapter, come and beſeech him that he will depart out of their coaſts; that ſo, if it were poſſible, they might never more ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear or think of him.</p>
            <p>But you will reply, Why, do you think that any are ſo wicked, as to thruſt God from them, or to baniſh him out of their thoughts? or if they would, were it poſſible for them ſo to do?</p>
            <p>I might, I confeſs, frame two Objections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what hath been ſaid in this Uſe: and for the more methodical improvement of the Point, I don't care if I do: and to theſe onely I ſhall ſpeak at preſent, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, concerning the impoſſibility of Gods departure from a wicked man; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle arguing with thoſe at <hi>Athens,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.27, 28. <hi>He is not far from any of us,</hi> good or bad: how then can wicked men put God from them?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: Though wicked men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put themſelves far from the eye and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, he being Omniſcient and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent; yet may they put God far from their thoughts: though they may ſee God in their Conſciences, yet they never found him in their Affections. As wicked men are far from the favour and love of God, ſo are they far from love and affection to God. God may be and is neer them, in regard of his common and general pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152468:60"/>but they do not deſire the ſpecial preſence of God in their hearts; that is a burden to them: and hence 'tis that they <hi>ſay in their hearts, that there is no God,</hi> Pſal. 14.1. <hi>The fool,</hi> i. e. the vile, wicked, and worthleſs perſon, <hi>ſaith in his heart that there is no God.</hi> A fools bolt, we ſay, is ſoon ſhot: it may be he doth not always ſpeak it with his mouth; but his heart ſpeaks it; he thinks there is no God: with theſe wicked ones before my text, he denies the Attributes, Ways, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Providence, and Service of God, whatſoever is included in the whole Name of God: he ſaith, <hi>'Tis in vain to ſerve the Lord, and there is no profit in ſeeking to him.</hi> So that, I ſay, 'tis clear, that though wicked men cannot put themſelves out of the intuition and inſpection of God, yet they may and do put themſelves far from the thoughts of God, and from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Name.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, it will be objected, Are any ſo wicked, as to forget God? are there any ſo vile, as to put the Name of God out of their thoughts?</p>
            <p>Yes, Beloved, that there are: every wicked man doth it more or leſs: ſo <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks in the fore-mentioned text, <hi>Job</hi> 21.14. <hi>They ſay unto God, Depart from us: for we deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy ways.</hi> He ſpeaks of wicked men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely; of all, yea, of every wicked man: every wicked man ſaith to God, <hi>Depart from me.</hi> This I could evidence to you in ſundry paſſages and practices of wicked men: but for brevity ſake, I will exemplifie onely in that one ſet down in that text, <hi>Job</hi> 21.12. Wicked men make it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152468:61"/>appear that God is not in all their thoughts, becauſe they deſire not the knowledge of his ways. As the ways of a wicked man are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways grievous to God; ſo are the ways of God always grievous to wicked men; therefore they deſire no acquaintance with, no knowledge of them: they are a very loaching to their ſouls; they are rough, ſharp, ſad, and unſuitable to their ſpirits and genius: Wicked men, as they think, are provided of better ways, of ways more eaſie, ſmooth, plain, pleaſant; and therefore they have no manner of deſire to Gods ways: <hi>we deſire not the knowledge of thy ways.</hi> The word in the Hebrew ſignifying <hi>deſire,</hi> is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred alſo to <hi>take pleaſure</hi> or <hi>delight</hi> in; becauſe thoſe things which we delight in, are moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by us: and when they ſay, <hi>We deſire not the knowledge of thy ways,</hi> more is intended then the bare negative of their deſire: we may reſolve this Negative into an Affirmative, thus: We diſlike, yea, we hate the knowledge of thy ways. But what are thoſe ways of God which finde ſo little acceptance &amp; entertainment with wicked men? In general, by the ways of God, he intendeth not thoſe ways in which God walketh; but thoſe which God hath made for man to walk in; as namely, the ways of his providence and outward adminiſtrations; the ways of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, or thoſe rules of life in and by which we ought to walk, and regulate our whole courſe, the ways of his Works, the ways of his Word; the ways of his Worſhip; wicked men deſire not the practical or experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe. And thus much of the firſt Uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:152468:61"/>I come to a ſecond Uſe, and that ſhall be a Uſe of Increpation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it ſo, <hi>that it is and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and upon the things of God?</hi> This Point looks ſadly and ſowrely upon ſuch as think baſely, unworthily, and diſhonourably of God: upon ſuch, who, in ſtead of holy and heavenly, entertain atheiſtical, blaſphemous, unbelieving, and rebellious thoughts. I ſhall give a touch upon each of theſe, and ſo come to a third Uſe.</p>
            <p>Some have groſs, earthly, and terrene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of God; they become <hi>vain in their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> about him, as thoſe ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.23. Thus ignorant perſons, who fancy God to be ſome old man ſitting in heaven, with a Crown on his head, and a Scepter in his hand, adminiſtring his kingdom as an earthly Prince. Others, though they conceive God to be a ſpirit, and not a bodily ſubſtance; yet they in their thoughts rob him of his eſſential and inſeparable Attributes. 1. Some deprive him of his Omnipreſence, thinking that God is not preſent in all places; <hi>David</hi> could ſay, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7, 8, 9, &amp;c. <hi>Whither ſhall I go from thy ſpirit? or whither ſhall I flee from thy preſence? If I aſcend up into heaven, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there. If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea,</hi> &amp;c. but now, wicked men, on the other ſide, are brought in ſpeaking of God, as if he were ſhut up in heaven, and had nothing to do in the world. <hi>Job.</hi> 22.12, 13. <hi>Is not God in the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152468:62"/>height of heaven? and behold the height of the ſtars, how high they are. And thou ſayeſt, How doth God know? can he judge thorow the dark cloud?</hi> So again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44 7. Some deny in their hearts his Omniſcience, as if God did not know all the tranſactions of men. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.11. <hi>David</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wicked mans thoughts, tells, <hi>He hath ſaid in his heart, God hath forgotten; he hideth his face, he will never ſee it.</hi> So much the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> inſinuateth, in that wo which he denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth againſt wicked men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.15. <hi>Wo unto them that ſeek deep to hide counſel from the Lord, and their works are in the dark, and they ſay, Who ſeeth us, and who knoweth us?</hi> Some deprive God of his juſtice, thinking that although they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the practice and often repetition of ſin, yet God will not puniſh them according to the cominations and threatnings of his Word. If you doubt whether or no there be any ſuch ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination in mans heart, reade <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>And it come to paſs, when he heareth the words of this curſe, that he bleſs himſelf in his heart, ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of mine heart, to adde drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to thirſt.</hi> Nay, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 10.3. <hi>The wicked boaſteth of his hearts deſire, and bleſſeth the covetous, whom the Lord abhorreth:</hi> or, we may reade it, <hi>The covetous bleſſeth himſelf:</hi> So much is implied in that of the Lord unto the Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>Will ye ſteal, murther, and commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and burn incenſe unto Baal, and walk after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods, whom ye know not; and come and ſtand before me in this houſe, which is called by my Name, and ſay, We are delivered to do all theſe abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:152468:62"/>Some again think unworthily of God, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying his providence, whereby he ordereth and diſpoſeth of all things in the world; as if God regarded not his people; as if he cared not which way things go. So did theſe wicked ones above my text: ſo did they of whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zephaniab</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12. <hi>that ſay in their heart, The Lord will not do good, neither will he do evil.</hi> Others again rob God of his purity and holineſs; they conceive God to be wicked as themſelves are, becauſe he keeps ſilence at their ſins: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. or elſe becauſe he doth not preſently execute wrath upon ſin and ſinners, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11. Others, and not a few, conceive God to be made up altogether of mercy: they think he will ſave them, and not deſtroy the works of his own hands, though they live never ſo wickedly. Others deny the truth of God, and make him a lyer; as if God would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh either what he hath promiſed to his people, or threatned againſt his enemies: ſo did thoſe wicked ones of whom the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. Others, in the laſt place, do not onely think baſely and unworthily of God; but they think thoughts againſt him, ſuch thoughts as are directly oppoſite to his Name: they take up high and haughty imaginations, ſuch as exalt themſelves againſt the knowledge of God, and obedience of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: of which thoughts you reade, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. Nay, they have thoughts of high treaſon, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen rebellion againſt heaven; ſaying as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his voice?</hi> or as they, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 12.4. <hi>With our
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152468:63"/>tongue we will prevail; our lips are our own: who is lord over us?</hi> or as they, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.15, 16, 17. <hi>As for the word that thou haſt ſpoken unto us in the Name of the Lord, we will not hearken unto thee: but we will certainly do whatſoever thing goeth forth of our mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Beloved, and many other ways which I might name, do wicked men think diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of God. Now, as I told you in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Uſe, the Doctrine which I have in hand looks very wiſhly and ſowrely upon all theſe. As it excludes them out of the ſociety of the fearers of God, ſo it brings them under heavy wrath, guilt, and puniſhment. God will one day diſcover and lay open before the whole world, angels and men, thoſe vile thoughts that wicked men have had of him, and againſt him, in their hearts: he will ſet their iniquities in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before them, and their ſecret ſins in the light of his countenance; as 'tis, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.8. he will bring every one of theſe ſecret thoughts into judgement, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.14. And that none might be ignorant of this, he makes proclamation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as it were in open Court, by the voyce of his holy Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.19. I deſire all thoſe that are guilty of ſinful thoughts againſt God, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this text well, and to lay it home unto and upon their hearts this evening: <hi>Hear, O earth: behold, I will bring evil upon this people, even the fruit of their thoughts.</hi> The heavy wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Almighty God, is both the juſt deſert, and the certain iſſue and event of evil thoughts: inward diſtempers, and mental abominations, ſhall not go unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:152468:63"/>And this ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Uſe, the Uſe of Increpation. I proceed to a third, and ſhall make what progreſs in it the ordinary time will give me leave; and that ſhall be a Uſe of Trial and examination to every one that hears me this evening.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it ſo, <hi>that it is and ought to be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon God, and upon the things of God?</hi> Let then every man and woman learn hence to make an eſtimate of his and her ſpiritual eſtate, by the quality and diſpoſition of their thoughts. For 'tis moſt certain, that as the man is, ſuch are his thoughts; and as the thoughts are habitual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ordinarily, whether good or evil; ſo is the man. Thoughts are called the <hi>poſſeſſions</hi> of the heart, <hi>Job</hi> 17.11. <hi>The thoughts of my heart:</hi> in the Original 'tis, <hi>the poſſeſſions of my heart.</hi> Now they are called <hi>poſſeſſions of the heart,</hi> two ways: 1. In a paſſive, and 2. in an active ſenſe. Paſſively, becauſe thoughts are poſſeſſed by the heart; the heart doth incloſe and hold our thoughts; the heart is the proper veſſel and receptacle of thoughts; the heart naturally is the ſoil and ſeat of thoughts: there they are planted, and there they dwell. And then they are the poſſeſſions of the heart actively: for as thoughts are poſſeſſed by the heart, ſo thoughts do poſſeſs the heart. Thoughts are full of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: they trouble, and they comfort the heart. Look what our thoughts are, ſuch is the eſtate of our hearts: if our thoughts be quiet, our hearts be quiet; if our thoughts be unquiet, our hearts be unquiet: if our thoughts be joyful, our hearts
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152468:64"/>rejoyce; if our thoughts be ſad, our hearts are ſorrowful. And therefore 'tis ſaid in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.38. <hi>Why are you troubled, and why do thoughts ariſe in your hearts?</hi> i.e. Why do trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, diſconſolate thoughts ariſe in your hearts? 'Tis as natural for thoughts to ariſe in the heart, as 'tis for water to riſe in a ſpring or fountain. Chriſt did not chide becauſe thoughts, but becauſe ſuch thoughts did ariſe in their hearts. We cannot hinder our thoughts from thinking, no more then we can hinder the fire from burning, or water from wetting. They are the poſſeſſions of our hearts; and being the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of our hearts, we may eaſily judge of our eſtate and condition by them. Purity in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, is the moſt ſound, and infallible evidence of our fearing God. Whatever evil is practiſed or committed in the life, proceeds from the heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. <hi>For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts,</hi> &amp;c. So again on the other ſide, whatever good is acted in the life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the heart: <hi>Out of the heart,</hi> ſays So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, <hi>are the iſſues both of life and death.</hi> And therefore I ſay again, Examine your eſtate by your hearts, and by your thoughts, which are the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of your hearts.</p>
            <p>Now there are two ways how a man may try his thoughts: 1. By the cauſes of them; and 2. By the effects of them: A word or two of each, and ſo I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Try your thoughts by the Cauſes of them.</p>
            <p>Are they put in by God and his Spirit? doth the Spirit of God raiſe them up in your hearts; or elſe are they injected and caſt in by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil?
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152468:64"/>And ſo I might enlarge my ſelf, in ſhewing when our thoughts are formed and framed in us by the Spirit of God, and when thruſt in by the devil: but that would be a field too large for me: and therefore I briefly paſs it by.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Try your thoughts by the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of them. Are they holy, heavenly, and gracious? Carnal men are projecting how to ſpend their days and moneths in buying, in ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and getting gain: the fool in the Goſpel is thinking of enlarging his barns, of pulling down his houſes, and building greater, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.17, 18. this is that which engroſſed all his thoughts. One Apoſtle deſcribes ſuch men thus: <hi>Minding earthly things.</hi> Phil. 3.19. another thus: <hi>Having an heart exerciſed with covetous practices,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.14. <hi>With covetous practices,</hi> i.e. with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt contrivances how to promote their gain and earthly aims. But now men and women fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, they are for gracious projects; they are thinking how they may be more thankful; ſaying with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 116.12. <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits towards me?</hi> They are thinking how they may be more holy and ſpiritual, how they may be more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſerviceable to God, how they may be more fruitful in every good word and work. So that, I ſay, in the ſecond place, try your thoughts by the matter of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Try them from the form and faſhion of them. Are they notional, floating, and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental; or are they ſtudious, ſollicitous, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent thoughts? Do you ſit, as it were in the door of your hearts, on ſet purpoſe to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152468:65"/>good thoughts, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was wont to ſit in the door of his tent, to entertain ſtrangers; or do they fall in onely by the by, collaterally, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the intention? Theſe holy men in my text did not onely think upon Gods Name caſually, or by chance; but they did it ſeriouſly and in good earneſt, and ſtayed up their hearts againſt all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Examine your thoughts by the duration and continuance of them. Are your good thoughts fixed, ſetled, conſtant and permanent; or are they flitting, fugitive, tranſient, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary onely; as ſoon gone as come, like a flaſh of lighting in the air; like the ſtony ground, whoſe fruit was no ſooner ripe then rotten; or like the graſs upon the houſe top, which the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of, which withereth afore it groweth up? And then laſt of all,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Try your thoughts by the effects which they work in you. Do your thoughts of Gods preſence, purity, and holineſs, make you to tremble, and afraid to ſin; thoughts of his mercy and patience, lead you to repentance; the thoughts of his power and all-ſufficiency, work you to a cloſe, even, and uniform walking with God; the thoughts of heaven, wean you from the earth; the thoughts of the vanity of life, fit you for death? Do the thoughts of the inſtability and uncertainty of temporal things, edge and quicken your deſire after eternal things? Are your meditations driven to that iſſue which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> were, to make you turn your feet unto Gods Teſtimonies; to have reſpect to his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, to his Ways and Precepts? Are your
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152468:65"/>thoughts thus improved? are your thoughts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to ſuch holy ends &amp; purpoſes as theſe are? I beſeech you, when you come home, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with your own hearts, &amp; endeavor to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſomewhat of your eſtate and condition by your thoughts. And ſo much of this Uſe, and for this time. I proceed unto the fourth &amp; laſt Uſe of this Point, and that ſhall be for Exhortation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it ſo, that <hi>it is and ſhould be the practice of all them that truly fear God, to meditate diligently upon God, and the things of God?</hi> This Doctrine then calls upon all the true fearers of God, to be much in meditating and thinking upon his Name. And here, for the performance and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter performance of this great and neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſhall lay down before you in the firſt place ſome Motives; Secondly, ſome Means; and thirdly, ſome Rules or Directions.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Motives; and the firſt ſhall be taken from the neceſſity of the duty. 'Tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in a double conſideration: 1. in regard of God: 2. in regard of our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of God: he requires and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the duty. See what God ſaith to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Joſh. 1.8. <hi>This book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerve to do according to all that is written therein.</hi> One would think it ſhould rather have been ſaid, <hi>This book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy heart, but thou ſhalt, &amp;c.</hi> of if not ſo, then thus: <hi>This book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt ſpeak of it day and night.</hi> Meditation is too high a Muſe for the mouth. But, Beloved, becauſe there
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152468:66"/>ought to be much meditation about the Law of God, before a word of it comes out of the mouth; therefore the Lord ſaith, <hi>This book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night.</hi> The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it is this: As often as thou ſhalt ſpeak, thou ſhalt meditate; thou ſhalt not ſpeak raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: it ſhall not be the work of thy tongue alone, but of thy minde and tongue together. Now as in this text, the Lord requires holy conference, of which I ſhall ſpeak (God willing) in the next Point: ſo doth he likewiſe require holy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Thou ſhalt meditate therein:</hi> This carries with it the full force of a command. So again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.20, 21. <hi>My ſon, keep thy fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and forſake not the law of thy mother: binde them continually upon thine heart, and tie them about thy neck.</hi> The phraſe of ſpeech is borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Garments or Jewels. The meaning of it is: Lay them up as ſafe in your thoughts, tie them as faſt to your hearts, by holy meditation, as men do their clothes; nay, as they do their chains and jewels, to their bodies: or elſe deal with them, by frequent meditating upon them, as men do by thoſe things which they ſet down in their book or table, that ſo they may keep a preciſe memorandum of them. The like injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction you finde given, <hi>Phil</hi> 4.8. the text which I alledged in the confirmation of this Point. So again, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15. ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> there to <hi>Timothy, Meditate upon theſe things, give thyſelf wholly to them, that thy profitting may appear to all:</hi> What things? why, the things of God and bis Goſpel. So then, this duty is neceſſary in reſpect of Gods
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152468:66"/>poſitive and peremptory command.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this duty is neceſſary in reſpect of God, becauſe 'tis he that indued us with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſouls, with thinking faculties: 'tis he that hath given us an ability this way; I mean, an ability or faculty to think or meditate. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being.</hi> 'Tis in God that we move; I, and that with the motions of our mindes, no leſs then with the motions of our bodies: <hi>in him;</hi> i. e. by and through him, through his power and goodneſs, that we are acted and moved in our minds; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves: but our ſufficiency is of God.</hi> The Apoſtle, you ſee, inſtanceth in this very duty of thinking, and of holy meditation. 'Tis not in our own power to think, much leſs to think a good thought: all our ſufficiency this way is from God. Now then, if it be God, as you hear, that hath put into us thinking faculties; 'tis needful then that we ſhould return them back upon him again, by thinking ſeriouſly and induſtriouſly upon his Name. Nay, you ſhall finde, that upon this very ground, becauſe God hath given us our ſpirits, our ſouls, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral faculties of them; therefore we are to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him with them. This is evident, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. the later part of the verſe: <hi>Therefore glorifie God in your body, and in your ſpirits, which are Gods:</hi> q. d. your ſpirits as well as your bodies are Gods, therefore glorifie him in your ſpirits. And can we better glorifie God in and with our ſpirits, then by frequent thinking upon his Name? Nay,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:152468:67"/>Thirdly, conſider that God will account with us for our thoughts: we muſt one day be as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible or anſwerable to God for our thoughts and meditations, as for any other things or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents whatſoever: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. At that <hi>day of revelation</hi> (for ſo the day of account is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called in Scripture) we ſhall be made like a tranſparent, pellucid; and diaphanous body; and all ſhall be laid naked and open: the books of Gods Omniſcience and mans Conſcience ſhall be opened: thy ſecreteſt thoughts, thy moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, retired, and ſequeſtred meditations, ſhall be as legible in thy forehead, as if they were written with the moſt glittering ſun-beams up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a wall of Chryſtal. Not only mens words and actions, but their thoughts, are all in print in Heaven, and God will in that day read them aloud in the ears of all the World; although no heart in the earth be privy to them but their own. That is worth your diligent obſervation to this purpoſe, which you finde, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will manifeſt the counſels of the hearts.</hi> What are more dark or hidden then mens inward thoughts? we may call them <hi>hidden things of darkneſs:</hi> yet even theſe, will God bring to light, theſe will he make manifeſt at that day. The Apoſtle, as I conceive, ſpeaks this for the encouragement of the Saints; he encourageth them to the very duty I am now upon: though they have been called hypocrites, and diſgraced; though they have had the dirt of a thouſand ſcandals caſt in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152468:67"/>their faces, yet there is a day coming, when God will take an account of your thoughts; your reproaches ſhall be wiped away, and your think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Name of God ſhall be brought in open view.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly, as God will in juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe wicked men, for the evil and ſinful managing; ſo he will in mercy reward the fearers of his Name, for the right and holy management of their thoughts. When <hi>David</hi> entertained but a thought or purpoſe of building an houſe for God, although God forbade him to do it; yet he rewarded that thought and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of <hi>David,</hi> in his ſeed, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16. So when the Prodigal purpoſed with himſelf to return home to his Father, you may ſee how it was rewarded, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.18, 19, &amp;c. and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, in the text before alledged, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. later part of the verſe, <hi>Then ſhall every man have praiſe of God.</hi> What, every man? Will God praiſe thoſe who are praiſeleſs? will he praiſe the proud and covetous, the drunkards and unclean? will he flatter men in their ſin, and ſow pillows of commendation under their elbows? No: the Apoſtles meaning is, every man that is praiſe worthy, every good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man; every true believer, all ſincere and honeſt hearts, whoſe thoughts, counſels, and meditations, have been aright; every ſuch a man ſhall have praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee that this duty is neceſſary; as alſo, how many ways 'tis neceſſary in reſpect of God. This is evident likewiſe in the text that I am now upon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152468:68"/>But then in the ſecond place, this thoughtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon the Name of God is needful in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our ſelves. Hereby, in the firſt place, we ſhall evidence unto our own ſouls and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that we are men and women truly fearing God: This is in my text ſet down as the property or diſtinguiſhing character of holy and godly men, that they <hi>thought upon his Name:</hi> Nay, they are conjoyned inſeparably; they were ſuch as feared God, and <hi>thought upon his Name.</hi> Thoſe beaſts under the Law which chewed not the cud, and divided not the hoof, were not to be eaten of; they were unclean. I could give you divers ſignifications and applications of dividing the hoof, and chewing of the cud: <hi>Willet</hi> in his eleventh Queſtion upon this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, alledging many: I ſhall at preſent ſpeak one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that which conduceth to my purpoſe. The parting the hoof in twain, ſignifieth the right diſcerning of the Word and Will of God, when we are able to judge of it, not carnally, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually: 2. Chewing of the cud ſignified the ſerious meditation of the Name and Law of God day and night; which is the food of our ſouls. Well then, as thoſe beaſts were unclean which divided not the hoof and chewed the cud; ſo thoſe men and women are ſpiritually unclean, unholy, and unſanctified, who do not diſcern ſpiritual things, and often recal them to their mindes, to meditate or to ruminate upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This duty is needful in reſpect of our ſelves, becauſe thoughts are the original and principles of action; meditation is the riſe and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152468:68"/>fountain both of communication and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; of words and of practices: it cauſeth the ſtream or current of both theſe to run either clear or muddy. The progreſs or method to action is, you muſt know, in this manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Thoughts do excite and ſtir up the Affections; Affections do kindle upon Thoughts, as Tinder doth upon the ſtriking of a ſpark of fire.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Affections they carry and command the Will, even as windes do the ſhip.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Will commands all the inferior pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to execute or to put in act that which the Thoughts have ſuggeſted, the Affections ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded, and it ſelf accepted.</p>
            <p>Now then, foraſmuch as thoughts carry ſuch an influence and tendencie unto action, good Reaſon why we ſhould holily and religiouſly employ them.</p>
            <p>Thus far of the ſecond Motive to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I ſhall run over the reſt with more brevity, and proceed as far in them as the remaining time will give me leave.</p>
            <p>Well then, in the ſecond place, ſerious and diligent meditation upon the Name of God, as 'tis a needful, ſo 'tis an excellent duty, ſuch a duty as will transform us into the image of God, from glory to glory. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>But we all, with open face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolding as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, are chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the ſame image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> As we by looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the glory, holineſs, and excellencie of God; ſo likewiſe by meditating upon the glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152468:69"/>and excellencie of God, are changed into the ſame image: <hi>i. e.</hi> we are made conformable unto him, we receive as it were the engravings of holineſs upon our ſouls, by meditating upon the holy One. As by a good concoction and digeſtion, our meat is incorporated into, and aſſimilated unto us; ſo, by meditation, which is ſpiritual concoction, we are aſſimilated and made like unto that Name upon which we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate. We read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.29. that when <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had been with the Lord upon the mount, his face did ſo ſhine, that <hi>Aaron</hi> and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael were afraid to come nigh him. Beloved, as long as a man is in the duty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditation, as long as he is thinking upon the Name of God, he is with God, he is in communion and fellwoſhip with him: and Oh, this will ſet a gliſtering luſtre and brightneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his heart; it will cauſe the face of his heart to ſhine. Let me tell you, for your encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, that the way to be an excellent Chriſtian, is to be a holily contemplative Chriſtian. Holy meditation will render you, with the Kings daughter, <hi>all glorious within.</hi> I ſhall enlarge no more upon this.</p>
            <p>In the third place (and ſo I ſhall conclude for the preſent) Holy meditation is a ſweet and comfortable exerciſe. <hi>David</hi> met with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fatneſs, honey and honey-comb, yea, with ſurpaſſing delight and pleaſure in this duty: and therefore ſaith he, (<hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.17.) <hi>How precious are thy thoughts unto me, O God! how great is the ſum of them!</hi> We may take the words two ways: 1. <hi>How precious are thy thoughts!</hi> i.e.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152468:69"/>how ſweet and precious are theſe thoughts of mercy which flow from thy heart to me, which paſs from thy ſoul to mine? But this acceptation of the words is not for my preſent turn; and therefore in the ſecond place, you may take them thus, with Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> in his Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon the place: <hi>How precious are thy thoughts! i. e.</hi> The thoughts that I have of thee, the thoughts that are raiſed out of my heart up to thee; Oh how precious are they! Divine meditation (Beloved) is a very heaven upon earth; 'tis an having of one foot already (if I may ſo ſpeak) in the porch of heaven; 'tis a fore-taſte of eternal life: 'tis to the Saints, as the fiery chariot was to <hi>Elijah;</hi> by it they are tranſported from earth to heaven in their ſpirits; nay, ſo far raviſhed in their thinking upon Gods Name, as that ſometimes they know not thoſe things that are before them, they minde not thoſe perſons that are about them; but being in the body, they are as it were carried out of the body, with ſpiritual raviſhment: they taſte ſuch incomparable ſweetneſſes in the good Name of God, as that they are not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them: even as the chewing of our meat makes us to taſte much more ſweetneſs in it; ſo this heavenly practiſe of meditation cauſeth us to feel much more ſweetneſs in the Name of God. Meditation ever brings with it delight: therefore ſee how <hi>David</hi> doth knit them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Pſalm 119.15, 16. <hi>I will meditate in thy precepts, and will have reſpect unto thy ways. I will delight my ſelf in thy ſtatutes; I will not forget thy Word.</hi> That holy object about which a mans
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152468:70"/>thoughts are much converſant, he cannot but take much delight and complacencie in. As it argues love to the object, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.97. ſo, I ſay, it argues delight in the object.</p>
            <p>And then, in the laſt place, to conclude the Motives; this is an exceeding profitable and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous duty; and that divers wayes: I will name onely two or three of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Meditation turns the promiſes into mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: it not onely taſteth, but cheweth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and manifeſtations of God unto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and therefore 'tis not onely ſweet and comfortable, as I told you before; but it is profitable too. Read <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.5, 6. <hi>My ſoul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs, and my mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyful lips: when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee upon my bed, and meditate on thee in the night-watches.</hi> As there is all manner of pleaſure, ſo is there all manner of profit in the believing meditations of God; they make the promiſes as a Royal feaſt to faith. Meditation is not onely an effect of faith, but 'tis an excellent means to ſtrengthen faith.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis profitable for the avoiding of evil: Meditation prevents the intruſion of vain and ſinful thoughts, of foul and fleſhly luſts; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would ſwarm in the ſoul: it leaves the devil no room for his black and helliſh ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for his blaſphemous injections. It defeats the world, which otherwiſe would be ready to catch us, to get in to defile our hearts.</p>
            <p>Nay, 3. It promotes our ſpiritual good: hereby we get into acquaintance with God, the fountain of all goodneſs: hereby we attain unto
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152468:70"/>a greater meaſure of ſpiritual wiſdom, grace, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; we prove tall and experienced Chriſtians, filled with all knowledge.</p>
            <p>Nay, this holy meditation, in a word, is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to others; for why? it fits us for holy and Chriſtian conference.</p>
            <p>Thus, and many other ways, is this Exerciſe profitable. Well then, you have heard what an encouragement there is to the practiſe of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. I come, in the next place, to ſhew you the means whereby you may be enabled to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it.</p>
            <p>The Means ſhall be of two ſorts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Negative.</item>
               <item>2. Poſitive.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By Negative, I intend thoſe ſins or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which we muſt labor againſt, if we will fruitfully think upon the Name of God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, avoid Pride, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs of a ſufficiencie in your ſelves to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God, or to think of any thing elſe that is good. You have heard before, what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. Pride hinders the right improvement of every holy duty, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in every holy duty. God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hath promiſed to impart himſelf and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets to the humble, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.9. but God will have no acquaintance with proud perſons; <hi>he looks upon them afar off,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks. This cauſeth a mans going out from God indeed, but it hinders his drawing nigh to God, as in other exerciſes, ſo in this of holy contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. God commonly leaves ſuch to doat and buſie their brains about Queſtions and vain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152468:71"/>which tend to nothing but ſtrife and oſtentation. See what the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a proud and ſelf-conceited man, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>He is proud:</hi> what follows? <hi>knowing nothing, but doating about queſtions, and ſtrifes of words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cometh envie, ſtrife, railings, evil ſurmiſings; perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that gaine in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. From ſuch withdraw thy ſelf.</hi> It is juſt with God, to leave proud hearts to unprofitable ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you will religiouſly meditate upon the Name of God, take heed, as of Pride, ſo of Paſſion: Paſſion carries us out of our ſelves, and carries us too from the buſineſs and duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us. As an angry mans diſcourſe runs wilde, ſo his thoughts and cogitations run wilde alſo. As the paſſions of the Concupiſcible appetite, and intemperancies of youth, carry a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his bounds; and therefore the Prodigal repenting, is ſaid to <hi>come to himſelf,</hi> Luk. 15.17. ſo likewiſe do the paſſions of the Iraſcible appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. Anger diſorders and diſcompoſeth the ſpirit. Paſſions in the minde, are like a tempeſt in the air, which do exceedingly diſturb the minde. Many a man, like a ſhip at ſea, hath been over-ſet and ſunk with the violent guſts and whirlwindes of his own ſpirit. As a turbulent heart can neither hear nor pray as it ought; ſo ſo neither can it think or meditate as it ought. Paſſion unfits the heart to and for any religious duty.</p>
            <p>Well may ſuch a one <hi>exact folly,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks; but I warrant you, while he is thus
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152468:71"/>diſtempered, he wo'n't lift up many holy thoughts; theſe do require a ſedate and quiet ſpirit, free from the confuſed hurrie of trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome paſſions. And therefore, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, ſee that you eſchew paſſion. And then</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you would conſcionably perform this duty, beware of earthly-mindedneſs. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs or earthly-mindedneſs divides and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts the heart, fills it with noyſome luſts; but indiſpoſeth it to the thinking of God, or upon the things of God. This corruption, if nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will eat all manner of goodneſs out of the heart. The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32, 33. <hi>But I would have you without carefulneſs. He that is unmarried, careth for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may pleaſe the Lord: but he that is married, careth for the things that are of the world, how he may pleaſe his wife.</hi> Implying, that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive and an immoderate engaging of the heart in the world, is one main cauſe why a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take care for the things of the Lord as he ought to do: ſuch a man, ſuch a woman, cannot attend upon the Lord in any duty, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. ſaith our Saviour there, <hi>No man can ſerve two maſters:</hi> i. e. two maſters of contrary intereſts, and who iſſue forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary commands. Every wicked man ſerves more maſters then two: he is a ſervant to luſt; yea, he ſerves <hi>divers luſts and pleaſures, Tit.</hi> 3.3. but yet he ſerves not that One, who is infinitely better, and more deſerving our ſervice then all: and ſerving Mammon, he cannot ſerve God as he ought, in any ſervice; and therefore not in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152468:72"/>that which I am now ſpeaking of. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. Set your affections on things above, not on things on the earth: <hi>q. d.</hi> If your thoughts run upon the things of the earth, they wo'n't carry you out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things above.</p>
            <p>And thus much of the Negative means, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the hinderances of this holy meditation. I come, in the next place, to ſpeak of the Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive helps: and with them I ſhall conclude this days publick Exerciſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you deſire to think upon the Name of God, then begin the day with the thoughts of him, and of his mercies renewed upon you, not onely every morning, but every moment. This ſeems to be <hi>Davids</hi> conſtant courſe, from ſuch texts as theſe are, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.13. and the like you may finde in many other places, that to begin with the thoughts of God in the morning, is the way to put the ſoul into an heavenly frame and temper the whole day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. We have a ſaying amongſt us, that <hi>the morning is a friend to the Muſes:</hi> Aurora Muſis amica, <hi>i. e.</hi> the morning is a good ſtudying time. I am ſure, the morning is a great friend to the Graces; 'tis the beſt time to begin our thoughts and meditations; it will diſpoſe the heart to and for communion with God all the day after. And withal, remember to cloſe up the heart with God, when you go to bed at night; and, if poſſibly you can, fall aſleep out of ſome heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditation. So will your heart be in a better plight when you awake. He that thus raketh up fire over-night, (as one ſaith) ſhall finde fire again in the morning. That is the firſt Means to the Duty in hand.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:152468:72"/>2. Guard and watch over your hearts all the day long, that they be not drawn from God, or from the thoughts of him, either by any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption from within, or temptation from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. <hi>Prov</hi> 4.23. <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence:</hi> defend it from all inroads and incurſions from the fleſh, world and devil. Keep but the heart well in tune, and then it will not ſo eaſily go out from God. Beloved, if you ſuffer your hearts to be ſcattered up and down, upon earthly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, it will be far to ſeek when you ſhould wait upon God, either in Prayer or Meditation; as a wilde horſe turn'd to range up and down into a wilde Common, that can hardly be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken when he ſhould be ſadled. As you ſhould be in the fear of the Lord all the day long; ſo ſhould you be raiſing, elevating, and winding up your hearts to God all the day long. You ſhould hold communion with God, even in the duties of your particular callings, and civil em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. ſaith the Apoſtle there, <hi>Our converſation is in heaven.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>converſation,</hi> in the Greek, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly rendred thus: <hi>Our civil life,</hi> or <hi>our civil converſation is in heaven:</hi> q. d. we exerciſe our general callings in our particular; we go about earthly buſineſſes with heavenly mindes; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting, by a Divine Alchymie, heavenly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of earthly objects and occaſions. And I conceive there is ſomething to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39. where he ſaith, <hi>Brethren, let every man wherein he is earth, abide with God.</hi> How doth a man abide, with God in his particular calling? not onely
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152468:73"/>by keeping within the bounds and limits of that calling wherein God hath placed him; but alſo executing the duties of it as in the ſight of God, by minding God in the ſeveral paſſages and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of it. This alſo is to abide with God in our calling: and this we muſt do, if we will be conſcionable to the duty enjoyned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Would you have your thoughts to be ſet upon the right object, upon God and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with theſe godly ones here in my text? Then hold a ſtrict hand over your thoughts: be often in and upon the examination of them. Evils, you muſt know, begin firſt in the thoughts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. <hi>For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, falſe witneſs, blaſphemies.</hi> Firſt, evil thoughts; and what then? murders, adulteries, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thefts, falſe witneſs, blaſphemies. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil thoughts are ſet in the front of this black Roll. When God would expreſs the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the old world, he ſaith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>That every imagination of the thoughts of their heart was onely evil continually.</hi> The imagination gives ſhape to every thing that the minde works up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The reaſon of Atheiſm, is Blaſphemy in the thoughts; the reaſon of worldlineſs, is ſome wicked thought that lies hid in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: and therefore ſaith God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts.</hi> You muſt not onely mark your <hi>way,</hi> but your <hi>thoughts:</hi> trace every corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, every inclination, every affection, every tranſient motion: whatever paſſeth thorow your hearts in the whole day, call it to an audit,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152468:73"/>ſet upon the tryal of it. Our thoughts are even infinite, nimble, ſlippery; and therefore we had the more need to watch them, and to ſet upon the ſearch of them; and having found of what nature they are, and of what tendencie they are; cheriſh the good, and check the bad. One e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil thought, one ſinful cogitation, being uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled, and given way to; O how may it vex and diſquiet our hearts, when we come to lie upon our death-beds! As David dealt with his wayes, ſo do you with your thoughts: <hi>I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered my wayes,</hi> ſaith he: ſo do you your thoughts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If you would think of God, and the things of God; then heighten your love to God, and the things of God. Strong affections make ſtrong impreſſions. and cauſe great thoughts of heart. A man cannot but think much of that which he loves much, and therefore ſaith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119. <hi>verſe</hi> 97. <hi>O how I love thy law! it is my meditation all the day:</hi> q. d. I do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly love thy law: I do love it ſo greatly, as that I cannot well expreſs how greatly I love it: <hi>O how I love thy law!</hi> and therefore 'tis, that I am ſo much in the meditation of it. Be ſure of it, that our infinite wandrings, and woful trifling away of our golden hours in idle and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil thoughts, is cauſed very much by our cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and luke-warmneſs in our love to God, and the things that are of divine concernment. Would we but prefer God, and the things of God, incomparably before all other things whatſoever: would we once make ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and heavenly things our chief portion and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152468:74"/>treaſure; then would our hearts be chiefly ſet upon them, and our thoughts moſtly run on them. See what our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.21. <hi>Where your treaſure is, there will your heart be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And then in the laſt place, to this end, make uſe of Prayer too. You know that God is both the heart-maker, and the heart-mender: deſire him to put your ſouls into a ſpiritual frame and temper; to direct your hearts unto the remembrance of his Name. Pray for your ſelves, as <hi>David</hi> did once for his people, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.18. <hi>Oh Lord God of Abraham. Iſaac, and Iſrael our fathers, keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people; and prepare our hearts unto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> In like manner, let us pray, Lord, keep thy Name for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of our hearts, and prepare our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: or as he prays, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 19.14. <hi>Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, be acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord my ſtrength and my redeemer.</hi> Pray that God would raiſe up your hearts, and raviſh your hearts; that you may ſo meditate upon his Name, that you may have reſpect unto all his ways.</p>
            <p>I ſhould come to give you ſome Rules or Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning this holy meditation: But of them (God willing) the next time.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe circumſtances bear ſuch a weight in every action, as that they either make or mar it; before I ſpeak of the form and manner of our think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Name of God, I ſhall deliver a word or two concerning the circumſtances of Meditation. There are two circumſtances to be heeded in this duty.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:152468:74"/>
               <item>1. The circumſtance of Time.</item>
               <item>2. The circumſtance of Place.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the circumſtance of Time. Though it cannot be denied, but that a Chriſtian ſhould have dayly converſe and communion with God; he ſhould be alwayes ejaculating and raiſing up of his heart to heaven, ſaying with <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 36.4. later part of the verſe: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my ſoul.</hi> Though he ought to take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, even from thoſe things which do occur and offer themſelves unto his outward ſenſes, to aſpire and climb up to God in his heart; yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, every Chriſtian ſhould redeem ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it and convenient portion of time, and ſet it apart from other employments, that ſo he may ſolemaly and ſeriouſly think upon the Name of God: he muſt not onely do it occaſionally, but he muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſome time or other on ſet purpoſe, that he may the more thorowly diſcharge this neceſſary duty: at which time he ſhould concentre, and draw as it were into one point, all the powers and faculties of his ſoul, and command them to attend this heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe, as much as may be, without diſtacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And I ſuppoſe, Beloved, it were no great task, to fetch in the practiſe of ſome of the holy men of God this way. <hi>Iſaac</hi> went out to meditate at the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63. 'Tis conceived, <hi>Iſaac</hi> did this uſually, though at this time peradventure more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, by reaſon of that important buſineſs he had in hand; which was his marriage. It ſeems that <hi>Iſaac</hi> did ordinarily go forth about even-tide (which was, ſaith Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> at the ninth hour of the day; with us, the third hour in the afternoon, about three of the clock) to meditate. This was
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152468:75"/>
               <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s ſet-time for meditation, as (I ſay) 'tis generally conceived. So <hi>David;</hi> the Name of God, and the Word of God, was his medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all the day, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.97. and in the night, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.55. yet there are ſome texts which lead us to think, that <hi>David</hi> had his ſet and ſolemn times for this purpoſe: amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I will inſtance onely in that one, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.18. the laſt words of the verſe: <hi>When I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, I am ſtill with thee.</hi> Some indeed refer this to the laſt reſurrection; and give out <hi>David</hi>'s meaning to be this: When I ariſe out of my grave, I ſhall be ſtill with thee, I ſhall ever be with the Lord.</p>
            <p>But we need not to force the text: as <hi>David</hi> had other ſet-times to meditate upon God, ſo the morning was one of them: When I awake out of my ſleep, or, as ſoon as I awake out of my ſleep, I am with thee in holy meditation. So that, Beloved, ye are not onely to maintain a conſtant communion with God in this duty; but there muſt be ſome time laid aſide on ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for this duty.</p>
            <p>The ſecond circumſtance that I ſhall ſpeak of, is the circumſtance of Place; and here, as I ſpake of the time, ſo I may ſpeak of the place for holy meditation: As at all times we ſhould think upon the Name of God, ſo in all places; not onely in this place appointed for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſervice of God, but in all other places; in your houſes, in your ſhops, and places of trading; at board, and at bed; at home, and abroad. But yet, for preventing of diſtraction, and conſidering that Satan is ready to take all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152468:75"/>againſt us, labouring might and main, by outward objects, to diſtract and divide the faculties of our ſouls with impertinent or unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable thoughts, yea with ſinful and corrupt thoughts; therefore I conceive it neceſſary, that the place where we meditate moſt ſeriouſly and ſolemnly, ſhould be retired and ſecret. The devil well knows how neer and familiar earthly things are to our ſenſes, and how remote and far diſtant heavenly and ſupernatural things are; therefore he would fain work upon our carnali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by preſenting earthly objects, and by them would fain convey to our hearts earthly-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; and ſo bereave us of the benefit of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. So that, I ſay, to prevent the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and malice of the devil, 'tis beſt, whenever we deſire in good earneſt to ſet upon this duty, to withdraw our ſelves into ſome private place, into our chambers, ſtudies, or cloſets. What our Saviour ſpeaks concerning the duty of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, we may apply unto the duty of holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. <hi>When thou prayeſt, enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy cloſet:</hi> ſo, when thou meditateſt, enter into thy cloſet; withdraw as much as may be from the noiſe and clutter of the world; do it as privately and reſervedly as may be. I might give you ſome inſtances for this too. <hi>Iſaac</hi> did it in the field, as you may finde in the text before alledged, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63. he was private in meditation and ſoliloquie. Upon this paſſage of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> I finde one to have this obſervation. <q>
                  <hi>Domitian,</hi> ſaith he, about the beginning of his Empire, uſually ſequeſtred himſelf from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany an hour every day; but did nothing the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152468:76"/>while, but catch Flyes, and kill them with a pen-knife: but <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſequeſtred himſelf from company, to a better-purpoſe; he improved his ſolitarineſs for deep meditation and ſolilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie. <hi>David</hi> performed this duty in his bed, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.6. and therefore ſaith he, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 4.4. <hi>Commune with your own heart upon your bed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I given you a word or two concerning the circumſtances that are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in and about this duty. Before I come to the form or manner of performance, I might ſpeak ſomething of the matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the duty. But I ſhall onely hint at this, becauſe I have ſpoken already to this purpoſe, in the opening of this part of the text, <hi>And thought upon his Name.</hi> That which we think upon, muſt be the Name of God. A little word, but of large extent. We muſt think upon all that is poſſible for us creatures to know of God: think upon his Eſſence, think upon his Attributes, Wiſdom, Power, Juſtice, Mercy, Infiniteneſs, Holineſs, Omniſcience, Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We muſt think upon his Ordinances, Ways, Word, and Worſhip; think upon his work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whether common to the world, as creation and providence; or as more proper and peculiar to his Church, as Election, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demotion, Juſtification, Sanctification. Upon theſe muſt we think, and whatſoever is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed under the Name of God.</p>
            <p>But I paſs by this, and come unto the more particular directions. I deſire you to obſerve theſe following Rules, in reference unto Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152468:76"/>1. Think upon God primarily, chiefly, and in the firſt place. Let the Name of God have the firſt-fruits of your thoughts: begin with God in the morning, as <hi>David</hi> did, in the place fore-alleadged, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.18 and as the Church did, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.9 <hi>With my ſoul have I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired thee in the night, yea, with my ſpirit within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will I ſeek thee early:</hi> i.e. I have not onely thought upon thee in my moſt retired thoughts; but thou haſt had my firſt, as well as my laſt thoughts: I ended with thee at night, and I began with thee in the morning. Oh Beloved, as 'tis a ſweet thing to cloſe our eyes, ſo 'tis our duty to open our eyes, and to begin the day with God. I ſhall not ſtand upon this, becauſe I ſpake ſomething to this purpoſe in the Means. That rule of our Saviour is general, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore holds here: <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. <hi>But ſeek ye firſt the kingdom of God, and his righteouſneſs:</hi> Let hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things or objects have the priority, ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, and principality in your thoughts. No doubt but 'tis lawful for us to think of our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary buſineſſes: but we muſt think of them in their proper place and ſeaſon; ſecondarily, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately, and in the ſecond place: Be ſure that God have the <hi>Primitiae</hi> and firſt-fruits of your thoughts. But in the ſecond place:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Think upon the Name of God ſollicitouſly and carefully, and with all your might. So much is implied in that word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.33. The word <hi>ſeeking</hi> includes pain, toil, and labor; not an idle velleity, or a ſupine and lazie wiſh. If we urge the extent of the word, it notes ſo to require or exact, as doth an importunate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152468:77"/>in the Schools, or a violent tormentor on the Rack. This Greek word implyeth the ſame that the Hebrew word <hi>haſhabh</hi> doth in my text: it carries with it, as I told you in the opening of this phraſe, the intention of the minde. I confeſs, that with <hi>Martha,</hi> we are apt to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our heads about many things, apt to tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moil our ſpirits with fretting, vexing, carking and corroding cares and thoughts of the things of this life; quite contrary to that Goſpel-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.31. &amp; <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. This, I ſay, we are prone and ready enough unto: Oh that we could but more largely, more affectionately, more carefully and induſtriouſly think upon the things of God! This is a duty of the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; yea, this is that <hi>firſt and great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, Thouſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy minde, and with all thy might.</hi> This duty of meditation upon the Name of God, requires much earneſtneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Practiſe this duty chearfully, readily and willingly: The worldly man needs not to be invited to minde his profit, the voluptuous man his pleaſure, or the ambitious man his honour: theſe they do naturally; and what men do na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, that they do freely and willingly. Oh but how many invitations and inducements muſt Chriſtians have to this duty! how averſe from it, how backward are we unto it! We can think of any thing more eaſily and readily, then we can think of God, and the things of God. I beſeech you that fear God to conſider, that God loves not to ſtrain upon any, neither regards he an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntary or unwilling ſervice. 'Tis ſaid indeed,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152468:77"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. later part of the verſe: <hi>God loveth a chearful giver.</hi> And what is ſpoken of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is as true of any other. God loves to ſee us ſet upon our duties chearfully, and with a willing minde: this is acceptable and delightful to him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 110.3. God expects a free and a Princely ſpirit from his people towards his ſervice: <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.5. A true worſhipper of God is not thruſt and driven on by an outward written Law; but findes a law written in his own heart. They who have felt the day of Divine power, are not acted by humane power, by the coerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ordinances of men; they are under no conſtraint, in this duty of meditation eſpecially, but that of the love of God, and of Chriſt. If God ſhall delight in what thou doeſt, let it be thy delight and recreation to think upon his Name. I muſt not ſtand long upon theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, becauſe I ſee the time haſteneth away. Well then, in the fourth place,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Think upon God ſoberly, not thinking to pry into Gods ſecrets further then he hath been pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to reveal them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. <hi>The ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God: but thoſe things which are revealed, belong unto us.</hi> This is one of thoſe places which in the Hebrew is marked with a ſpecial note, to the end that we ſhould take ſpecial notice of it. As we muſt not think of our ſelves beyond ſobriety, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. ſo neither muſt we think of God beyond ſobriety, or above what is written of him: if we do, we ſhall quickly loſe our ſelves, and be ſwallowed up in a Maze or Whirl-pool of errours. Ye may ſooner drain
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152468:78"/>the Ocean with a ſhell or ſpoon, then the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God, with our largeſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: <hi>Job</hi> 38.22. <hi>Haſt thou entered into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the ſnow? or haſt thou ſeen the treaſures of the hail?</hi> There are ſecrets in Nature, which were never entred into by Art: the treaſures of the ſnow and of the hail deſcend upon us; but we cannot aſcend into the treaſures of them. We cannot enter into natural things: how then ſhall we enter into ſpiritual? how ſhall we enter into, or our thoughts comprehend the God of ſpirits? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath propared for them that love him:</hi> and if the things that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for man, are not yet entred into his heart; how can God, who hath prepared theſe things, enter into his heart? And therefore be modeſt and ſober, keep within the bounds of the Word, in your divineſt contemplations.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Think of God ſpiritually. To frame any groſs, carnal, or earthly image of God in our mindes; or to repreſent him to our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, by the ſimilitude or likeneſs of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whatſoever; this is plain idolatry, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the ſecond Commandment. See what God ſaith, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut</hi> 4.15, 16, 17, 18. Nay, this was a chief part of their Helleniſm or Gentiliſm, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.23. However, this may be very helpful to us in our thoughts of God, to conceive of him as of God in Chriſt. Chriſt is, as the author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> tell us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>The brightneſs of his glory, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſs image of his perſon.</hi> Chriſt is as it were the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152468:78"/>ladder of aſcention, by which we may climb up ſafely unto God. Doubtleſs we may ſix our mindes upon the humane nature, in which the Godhead dwells bodily, and to which 'tis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally united. And under any other cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter or reſemblance, we may not think of God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Think upon God reverently: We are bid to ſerve him with fear, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2.11. <hi>i.e.</hi> with a holy, filial, and reverential fear. If we do not thus think upon his Name, we take his Name in vain; we defile and pollute his Name. Thus thoſe wicked Prieſts, ſpoken of in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Prophecie of <hi>Malachi,</hi> are ſaid to deſpiſe the Name of God, yea to pollute it: and why was it? why becauſe they thought that any thing was good enough for God, <hi>Mal</hi> 1.6, 7, 8. Beloved, the Name of God is a great, dreadful, and terrible Name; and therefore we had need to think of it with prepared hearts, and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed affections. While we think upon his Name, let us awe his Name, and dread his Name. But I can enlarge my ſelf no further, the time being paſt. And therefore, in the laſt place,</p>
            <p n="7">7. Perform this duty conſtantly: not onely primarily, ſollicitouſly, chearfully, ſoberly, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and reverently; but perpetually and conſtantly. Theſe godly ones here in thy text, as they did not confer together onely once or twice, but often; ſo they often thought upon the Name of God: they did it habitually, it was their uſual practice. We ſhould never give over thinking upon the Name of God, until our thinking upon his Name be impoved to and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152468:79"/>for practiſe. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3. ſaith the Prophet there, <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord: i.e.</hi> We ſhall experimentally know the Lord, if we ſhall proſecute knowledge, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with meaſures already attained.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for this Point, and for this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152468:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
